<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A just vindication of the armie wherein all that doubt may have large satisfaction, in relation to their late proceedings. As touching the cause, beginning, continuance, and their end therein. Or, a book entituled, The examination of the late passages of the armie (especially of the grounds laid down for their justification in their declaration, June 14. 1647). / Examined, refuted, by A. Warren.</title>
            <author>Warren, Albertus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 126 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97208</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W952</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E410_18</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204455</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863945</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863945</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116163</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97208)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116163)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 65:E410[18])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A just vindication of the armie wherein all that doubt may have large satisfaction, in relation to their late proceedings. As touching the cause, beginning, continuance, and their end therein. Or, a book entituled, The examination of the late passages of the armie (especially of the grounds laid down for their justification in their declaration, June 14. 1647). / Examined, refuted, by A. Warren.</title>
                  <author>Warren, Albertus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 51, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeere, 1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: The lawfulnes of the late passages of the Army.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber: [i.e. October] 12.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lawfulnes of the late passages of the Army.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116163:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A JUST VINDICATION OF THE ARMIE WHEREIN All that doubt may have large ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in relation to their late pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings.</p>
            <p>As touching the Cauſe, beginning, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and their end therein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR,</hi> A Book entituled, <hi>The Examination of the late paſſages of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi> (eſpecially of the grounds laid down for their Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in their Declaration, <hi>June</hi> 14. 1647) <hi>Examined, Refuted,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By A. WARREN.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Micah 2.1, 2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Woe to them that deviſe iniquity, and work evill upon their beds, when the morning is light they practiſe is, becauſe it is in his hand, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mal. 3.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And I will come near to you to judgment, and I will be a ſwift Witneſſe against — thoſe that oppreſſe the Hireling in his wages, the Widdow, and the Fatherleſſe, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Ipſae etenim leges cupiunt ut Jure regantur,</l>
               <l>In Republica max. ma conſervanda ſunt Jura Belli.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Yeere, 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:116163:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116163:2"/>
            <head>A full Vindication of the Armie.</head>
            <p>I Have a long time waited, and with waiting longed, to hear, or ſee ſomewhat proceed from ſome of the Army, in order to their own juſtification, (more able for ſuch imployment) and in Anſwer to the forementioned Book ſtyled, <hi>The lawfulneſſe of the late Paſſages of the Army, &amp;c. Examined.</hi> But hitherto my hopes have been fruſtrate, which hath forced me (unapt for ſuch a work) to crowd amongſt others, (not out of vain oſtentation) upon the common Theater' to each mans publick view; my ſincear indeavours aſpiring no higher, then to give ſatisfaction to my doubting friends, (if I can) next to that main mark, (whereunto relation ought chiefly, to be had, in all things) even the glory of God. I was at firſt incouraged hereunto by the opprobious and deſpitefull language I frequently heard in the mouths of divers ill-affected perſons, againſt the Army, and many times my ſelf being ſcornfully hit in the teeth, by the ſhewing of this, and ſuch like Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets unto me. And knowing well enough it can be no affront to Juſtice, to ſpeak the truth, in behalf of the condemned Innocent, (it no whit oppoſing the juſt Law of this Kingdom, nor right reaſon, which is (or ought to be) the ground of all Law, for <hi>Lex eſt ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Ratio</hi>) I have undertaken the inſuing diſcourſe. And as it is the greateſt glory, that any Nation, or People are inveſted with, to be under the Command, and Juriſdiction, of a ſound, impartiall, and well principled Government, and upon good grounds, not to fear ſlavery, vaſſalage, thraldom, a yoak too ponderous for any to puton, (eſpecially thoſe, who are born free, and have the very name of freedom written, in ſo fair a Character in their foreheads, <hi>(Ab O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigine)</hi> that it is conſpicious, to the whole univerſe, and the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Nations can read it as well as themſelves:) So, on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, for ſuch to lye tamely under the corrupt Conſtitution of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaving power, (being clothed from their creations, with admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Immunities, Nature her ſelf crowning them with ſo rich a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116163:3"/>and abhorring thraldom in any) is the greateſt obloquie, and brand of ſhame, ſorrow, and infamie, that can befall a free State, or Kingdom. Oppreſſion, injuſtice, and vaſſalage, is not, ought not, to be indured in any, by whomſoever, or howſoever impoſed, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abominated and deteſted by the ſacred Lawes, of Religion, Reaſon,<note place="margin">Roma Tybur amo vent ſu, Tybure Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam. <hi>Verg.</hi>
               </note> Nature, and Nations. It is a very ſad diſaſter, and a great ſign of inſtability, when men, and their principles differ upon every occaſion, nay ſometime without the leaſt viſible occaſion thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. I know no one place or text of Scripture, the truth whereof hath been better backt, and attended, in all foregoing ages, and our preſent times,<note place="margin">Obad. 7. ver.</note> with more credible teſtimonies of verity then <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> ſo often repeated Maxime, <hi>That thoſe of a mans own houſe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly prove his greateſt enemies.</hi> I ſhall not make any Application of this to the preſent oppoſer, only give me ſo much favour, as to tell you with all meekneſſe, that though you had not that relation to the Army, as ſerve the State with them in particular ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Field, yet that you ſhould pretend friendſhip when their hearts, and hands, were active, and ſucceſſefull in fighting for freedom, and now deſert and deny them, for deſiring the fruition of the ſame things they contended for, is no leſſe then a wonder to me; inſomuch, that (I fear) you, as well as others, in caſes of the like nature, and concernment do hoiſe ſaile, more for ſome private unhappy reſpect, then for publick good and intereſt; but beware leſt your unſound veſſell meet with rocks, and there God find you out to your ſhame. Will you give the Army leave to ſight, and ſpill their bloud, for the recovery of the juſt wholeſome Lawes of the Nation, and ſhall they not be permitted now to ſpeak for the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of them? Will you be a friend when they fight, and a foe when they have obtained, becauſe they deſire the reaſonable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of undeniable ingagements? Have not the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom cauſe to look about them, and ſuſpect, (yea and in time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent) a deſign, when men diſſent from the Army, becauſe their tongues concurre with their hearts, hands, and the end of their Commiſſion. But not to tarry any longer here; we will come to the preface or Introduction to your Examination, which in the firſt place you lay down thus;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the late Declaration from the Army, of</hi> June 14. 1647. <hi>had given ſatisfaction to all their friends (as it ſeemed to promiſe in the firſt line) I ſhould then have been ſilent, &amp;c.</hi> It was not the intent of that firſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116163:3"/>line, that the Declaration could without a bleſſing give ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto any, much leſſe to all their friends, for its not in the power of any (but God himſelfe) either to perſwade, or prevaile with the judgements of men, and the Declaration is but a meanes thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to tending: And that the Declaration (concluded on by his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> and his Councell of VVarre, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward read in the head of every Regiment in the Army, and at laſt conſented unto by the Officers and Souldiers thereof) did not give ſatisfaction (though intended for that uſe) to all their pretended friends, or reall enemies, is not through any inſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in the thing it ſelfe, which is to all rationall men ſatisfactory enough, conſidered as an inſtrument; but either their owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capability, ſtubborneneſſe, or ſelfe-ends, by which meanes they will not incline their eares to the truth thereof. Then you ſay, who have ever (untill ſome of their late proceedings) not onely had the Army in great eſteem and honour, but ſtudied and endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (according to my abilities and place) to bee ſerviceable to them: Truly Sir, for your pretended eſteeme and honour of the Army formerly, (whilſt it laſted) they were beholden to you; but it ſills me with admiration, that you were no more reall nor ſtable, and that your principles ſhould be ſo ſlippery, as degenerate from what they were, and your judgement ſo darkned, as to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the well-grounded purpoſes and principles of the Army: and what thoſe late proceedings of theirs ſhould be, whereat you take occaſion to with-draw your firſt love, I am altogether ignorant of, unleſſe becauſe the Army are (by divine power) contriving, how righteouſneſſe and peace might kiſſe each other, juſtice and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment run downe our ſtreets like a mighty ſtreame: and for your ſtudying to ſerve the Army, according to your place and ability, and not perſiſting therein, whilſt they in the whole progreſſe of this late buſineſſe, have not in the leaſt deſired ought, but what the Parliament in their many Declarations have faithfully promiſed, (I wiſh they had been as really performed, &amp; then our troubles had ceaſed) might be ſufficient cauſe of ſorrow and ſadneſſe unto you.</p>
            <p>And to ſpeake in juſtification of their very adverſaries, in this one reſpect I dare boldly affirme it, the Army have received more civill uſage, curteous reſpect, and affectionate expreſſions of love from them, then from many of the neare pretended friends of the Parliaments Cauſe; and this not out of any hopes they have, that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116163:4"/>the Army ſhould effect that at laſt, which at firſt they oppoſed, and the other partie ſtood for; or that they looke for any curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie or favour from them, more then what in conſcience and equity, they are bound to allow them; but meerly from the obſervation of their good ends, (whereof many are convinced) civill deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and honourable performances of Articles and Covenants, which merits no leſſe then cordiall affection from very Enemies. But now you ſay, all your glorying in them is turned into ſhame, and your prayers and praiſes to God for them, into mourning and aſtoniſhment: I had rather heare this were for the fore-cited rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to wit, your ſtrange revolting from the Kingdomes cauſe, then that you ſeem to mention, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſee that under the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall notions, and colours of Gods glory, and good intentions to the Liberties and peace of the people of this Nation, the late acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and practices of the Army, in diſobeying and oppoſing the Parliament (if perſiſted in) will appeare to be contrary to the Lawes of God and the Kingdome, and to their duty, truſt, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement to the Parliament of England, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I am ſorry the eye of your judgement is ſo much obſcured, and you ſo much miſtaken in the affaires and proceedings of the Army: Doth it derogate more from Gods glory, when the Army preſent their humble de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to the Parliament by way of Petition, then it did when they freely powred forth their blood againſt the ſtubborne Adverſaries of our Tranquillity and Freedome? Are the good intents of the Generall to the Liberties and peace of this Nation, leſſe good, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath gained them <hi>(vi &amp; Armis)</hi> from the irreconcilea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enemies thereof, and now deſire the enjoyment of them for the Nation, from thoſe who arbitrarily and unjuſtly detaine them? Is it more diſobedience or oppoſition in the Army, to demand the price of their blood, even their hardly gotten Liberties of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, then it was in the Parliament at firſt to raiſe warre againſt the King? The Army might ſay to the Parliament in relation to their late proceedings, as they ſaid to the King at the beginning of this unhappie fraction;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is a levying of warre againſt the King, when it is againſt his Lawes and Authorities,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Book Dccl. part 1. pag. 276 where by the Statute of 25. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>though it be not immediately againſt his Perſon and the levying of force againſt his perſonall commands, though accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with his preſence; if it be not againſt his Lawes and Authority, but in maintenance thereof, is not levying warre againſt the King,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116163:4"/>but for him, &amp;c.</hi> So (and no otherwiſe) it is diſobedience and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition againſt the Parliament, when it is againſt their Lawes and Authorities, though it be not immediately againſt their perſons; and diſobedience and oppoſition to their perſonall commands, though accompanied with their preſence, if it be not againſt their Lawes and Authorities, but in maintenance thereof, is not diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and oppoſition to the Parliament, but the defence of the Parliament and their due Priviledges: In the judgement of any ingenuous man, that which you call diſobedience and oppoſition in the Army, is no more then what the King called Rebellion in the Parliament, and their actions then will appeare as contrary to the Lawes of God and the Kingdome, and to their duty, truſt, and ingagement to the King and Kingdome of England, as the preſent progreſſions of the Army will to the Parliament of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland; for it is evident to all the world, that the Army are gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the very ſelfe-ſame principles now, that the Parliament were grounded on at the beginning of this unhappy diſtraction;<note place="margin">Novemb. 2. 1646. Declar. 1 par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 696 &amp; page 150.</note> obſerve but their owne expreſſion, <hi>That obedience binds not men to cut their owne throats, &amp;c.</hi> had the Army obeyed the groundleſſe perſonall Commands of the Parliament, how unhappie had both themſelves and the whole Kingdom been? The Parliament at firſt alarumed the whole Kingdom, crying, Arme, arme, arme, with bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Drums, and ſoundings of Trumpets, (the ſad precurſors of inſuing War, and woe) aſſuring the people, the King, and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell then, intended to deſtroy their Religion, ſubvert their Lawes, enſlave themſelves, &amp;c. Whereupon the people ſuddenly ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a defenſive Martiall poſture for the Parliament againſt the King; and both parties reſolved, and to that purpoſe declared, to ſtand by each other, in ſafe-guarding their Freedoms, &amp; immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, (the juſteſt cauſe of any War,) whereupon, an Army was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meadiatly ſent forth, who took upon them to reſtore (or loſe their lives) the peoples Freedoms; this being done, and liberty purchaſed with the effuſion of bloud, were it not perjury, and perfidiouſneſſe in the Army, to ſuffer ſome Members of Parliament (after all this) to inthrall the people, and undo themſelves? Which was evident enough they would have done, (had they power anſwerable to their malice) as appears by Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> who was heard to report, when the Army but intended to Petition for their dues, That it was come to that paſſe, that either the Army muſt down, or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116163:5"/>They, meaning himſelf and his corrupt Rivals, muſt downe.</p>
            <p>And if the Armies refuſing to forfeit for ever their own and the Kingdoms freedomes, and ſurrender it, though earned with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valuable price of their deareſt bloud, to an inconſiderable party, of Arbitrary, mercileſs men, in both, or either Houſe of Parliament, be diſobedience, and oppoſition, as you terme it, to the whole, then how will you define obedience? Do you imagine the Parliament cannot oppreſſe? And if they do, muſt not eaſe be petitioned for, but for ſo doing the Petitioners muſt be accounted diſobedient, and oppoſers? Parliaments were called for the benefit, and not diſ-eaſe of the people.</p>
            <p>There are ſeverall things,<note place="margin">Four cauſes of a Parliaments being</note> which are chiefly the conſiderable Cauſes of a Parliaments Being;
<list>
                  <item>1 The out-cries of a free people inſlaved, to their King, for his Summons.</item>
                  <item>2 The Kings Summons, for the calling of a Parliament.</item>
                  <item>3 The peoples Election of their Members.</item>
                  <item>4 The Members appearance (upon the foreſaid Summons and the peoples Election) to any place appointed by the King, for to order, and diſpoſe of the great Affairs of the Kingdom.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Now when this Aſſembly thus lawfully gathered, ſhall forget the ends of their Conſtitution, and not rectifie, or cauſe to be recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, the known wrongs, and greivances of the People, and reſtore liberty to the enſlaved, the people may, (and are bound thereunto by the Lawes of Religion, Reaſon, Nature, and Nations,) ſue, and Petition for their juſt rights. Neither have the Parliament power to Act,<note place="margin">Ier. 38.5.</note> or order any thing but that which tends to the mutuall good and known weal of the people. If King <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> by his own confeſſion, could not impriſon a man, without, or againſt the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of his Princes, then by what Law, can the King, or Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> or both together, aſſume ſuch a power to themſelves, as bereave the people of their liberties, and birthrights? The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this Nation, and ſo the Army as a ſubſtantiall part thereof, being equally born free, may refuſe obedience to any Acts, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of King, or Parliament, whoſe apparent tendency is to their own ruine, and overthrow: and if it be ſo, that the Kingdom, and Army, muſt neither refuſe obedience to unjuſt commands, nor Petition for redreſs of manifeſt wrongs, (without being branded with diſobedient, oppoſers, infringers of the peace of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116163:5"/>and enemies to the State, and that which will be the ſad conſequence of all theſe, even the whole Kingdome and Army ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the limitleſſe pleaſures of mercileſſe men, whoſe tender mercies (as the wiſe man ſaith) are cruell, then farewell indeered Freedomes for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But to this you will happily object, Who ſhall judge when the Acts of the Parliament be deſtructive to the people?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In this caſe I know, at preſent, no better judge then their owne common and frequent experience, that undergo op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and wrong; who can better informe a man that he hath loſt the uſe of one of his joynts or members, then he that wants it?</p>
            <p>But not to ſtay longer here, I ſhall proceed to your next clauſe, to wit, <hi>by</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Parliament.</note> 
               <hi>whoſe Commiſſion they are an Army, and are but a tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous number of men; when they act or do any thing that is not in order to or within the limits of that Commiſſion, which I take to bee, the utmoſt bounds of their calling as an Army: and when any man or number of men, ſtep out of their calling, or if in their calling run out into by and unwarrantable waies, they can upon no good grounds looke either for protection, or expect a bleſſing, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true, it was by the Parliaments Commiſſion and none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers they were an Army; yet that was not the onely cauſe of their being an Army, but ſomething in relation to the Kingdome in generall, and ſomething alſo in relation to themſelves in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular: and therefore obſerve theſe things conſiderable in the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and levying of a lawfull Army.<note place="margin">Three things to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of a lawful Army.</note>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The lawfulneſſe of the Cauſe.</item>
               <item>2. The lawfulneſſe of the Call or Commiſſion.</item>
               <item>3. The collection or gathering together of the people in a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable poſture.</item>
            </list>
            <p>For the cauſe of raiſing this Army, it was the preſervation of His Majeſties Royall Perſon, and Kingdome, reſtauration of our almoſt loſt Lawes and Liberties, defence of the juſt Rights and Priviledges of Parliaments, &amp;c. their Commiſſion was from the Parliament, and their collection from themſelves freely and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly without conſtraint, or force, and this laſt they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced and provoked unto by vertue of the two former, to wit, the Cauſe and Commiſſion; all which have a neceſſary dependence each on the other, and are inſeparable in the levying of a lawfull Army; inſomuch that a Commiſſion without the peoples free
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116163:6"/>conſent, cannot raiſe an Army, nor both of them (as ſome have untruly ſaid) make a lawfull Army, without a lawfull Cauſe.</p>
            <p>And now I appeale to you and the whole Kingdome, if the Army have not to their power, inviolably obſerved, and with the price of their blood, effected the ſubſtantiall end of their Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which was for the defence of the Kingdome, &amp;c. as their owne Ordinances import,<note place="margin">Ordin. Feb. 15 1644. &amp; Apr. 1. 1645.</note> and if ſome diſ-affected Members in both or either Houſe of Parliament, did betray the confidence and truſt repoſed in them, and by their too effectuall inſluence on o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, (who perchance have no great deſires to cloſe with, or can diſcerne their baſe ends therein) ſo carry on their deep and darke deſignes, that the Kingdome ſuffers too much prejudice by them: muſt this conſtraine the Army to doe ſo likewiſe? Shall none be ready to ſtand in the gap in behalfe of this almoſt ruined King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſtop that inevitable inundation of miſery ready to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelme us through the inhumane malice of thoſe who make their luſt their Law? Is there no meanes left of freedome from Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian Task-maſters? Was it lawfull for the Army to oppoſe vaſſallage and thraledome to the death in the Kings party, and ſhall they ſo eaſily ſubject themſelves, and by their meanes the whole Kingdome to a farre worſe tyranny in ſome Members of Parliament? Or ſhall they out-ſtrip their Commiſſion, which is juſt and equitable, which is ſtill in force till the ends thereof bee performed by the Parliament as well as by them, and now run themſelves into extravagant courſes of Injuſtice and Tyranny, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe others doe ſo? Muſt they bid adieu to their Commiſſion and the fruits of their labours, becauſe they have laboured, and thoſe who gave them their Commiſſion command them? But I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort this aſſertion into your owne boſome againe thus:</p>
            <p>The Parliament are a Parliament by the Kings Warrant and the Peoples Election, for hearing complaints and redreſſing wrongs in the Kingdome: But when they act or doany thing that is not in order to or within the limits of that Warrant or Commiſſion, unleſſe they pretend a Commiſſion limitleſſe, as the ſequele of your diſcourſe imports, and tending alſo to the peoples benefit, by whom they were choſen, which I take to be the utmoſt bounds of their calling, as a Parliament, they are but a tumultuous number of men, and though any particular man, or number of men in the Parliament, ſtep out of their calling, or if in their calling run
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116163:6"/>out into by and unwarrantable waies, they can upon no good grounds, that I know of, either looke for protection, or expect a bleſſing.</p>
            <p>And then, as you import in the next place, however ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings being back't with policy and power, may have ſucceſſe at preſent, yet they are ſure to be bitterneſſe in the end.</p>
            <p>For the reſt of your Exordium or Introduction into your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe or pretended Examination, I ſhall leave as impertinent, my ordinary imployments not favouring me with time enough to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine every thing.</p>
            <p>Now to the firſt part of your Examination of the Armies De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, where you affirme,</p>
            <p>That although as particular Engliſh-men, they may petition or plead for what they thinke makes for the right, freedome, peace, and ſafety of themſelves and the Kingdome; yet they cannot doe it as an Army, for that relates onely to thoſe uſes (for which it was made) limited within Commiſſion: of your Aſſertion, I make a triple dividend, the affirmative and negative parts, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the latter.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In your affirmative part you grant all I deſire, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore needs no further trouble, to wit, <hi>that as particular Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men the Army may petition or plead for what they thinke makes for the right, freedome, peace, and ſafety of themſelves and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. In your ſecond or negative part you affirme, <hi>they cannot doe it as an Army.</hi> To which I anſwer:</p>
            <p>If not as an Army, then not at all; but their being an Army layeth ſeverall ingagements on them to petition.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The violence, oppreſſion, and injuſtice done to the people, in not hearing, and granting their juſt deſires and Petitions, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable commitments, illegall levyings of moneyes, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paying them for the uſes pretended, nor at all accounting for them, with divers other galling preſſures, which conſtraine the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, as an Army, to plead and petition for the Kingdome and themſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The cries and dolefull clamours of many thouſands, diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed people in ſeverall Counties of this Kingdome, abuſed, reviled and rejected by their ill-affected Truſtees in Parliament, inforceth them to plead as an Army; which ſaid people, after the preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116163:7"/>of divers humble Petitions, yet refuſed, though by due courſe of Law, reaſon, and honeſty, they ought and are bound in conſcience not onely to receive them, but make report thereof, and give effectuall anſwers thereunto, know no other meanes left them under the Sun, for the obtaining their juſt but loſt Liberties, except this Army, as an Army, in which caſe they make a law of neceſſity,<note place="margin">Neceſſitas non habet Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem.</note> which is without law, and exemption from vaſſallage, their reaſonable ſuit.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Their very Commiſſion in a double reſpect, doth inforce them as an Army hereunto, which might ſufficiently ſatisfie any rationall conſcientious man, in relation to their late proceedings; though no more were ſaid of it.<note place="margin">Reaſons why their Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion warrants them.</note>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Beecauſe they received it from the Parliament.</item>
               <item>2. They received it from the Parliament by, and according to Law.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, they received it from the Parliament, who are a lawfull Parliament, and ſo to be obeyed whilſt they act and order, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Lawes that made them ſo, and in order to the ſpeciall ends of their being and conſtitution.</p>
            <p>They received it from the Parliament by and according to Law, and ſo are injoyned by Law, to obſerve the commands and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions of the Law therein, and to compaſſe the ends of the ſaid Commiſſion, according, and not againſt or without Law, though the Parliament themſelves ſhould ſeverely require it: And if this were not ſo, the Army muſt and ought to infringe and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the Law, and conſequently for get the meaning and ends of their Commiſſion, becauſe they do ſo from whom they received it. It ſtands not with reaſon that you or I ſhould act the parts of mad-men or fooles, becauſe ſome, and thoſe eminent wiſe men and nearely related to us, have done ſo before us.</p>
            <p>The principall part of their Commiſſion I have before rehearſed, which is, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or defence of the Kingdome, according to the fore-quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Ordinances: whereby it is evident, that if the Army by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of that Commiſſion, are bound to defend the Kingdome, which is the utltimate end thereof, then are they obliged alſo, to the defence of every particular member in the Kingdome, without limitation of time, or reſpect of perſons; and if the Army may defend the Kingdome againſt the incroachments and inroads made by the King upon our Liberties and Franchiſes, (he being the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116163:7"/>Superiour Magiſtrate in the Kingdome, whilſt guided and biaſſed by Law) then doubtleſſe they may as reſponſibly defend it againſt the uſurpations of the Parliament, when their actions run in the corrupt channell of the peoples vaſſallage, ruine. And in caſe the Parliament refuſe to give the oppreſſed protection and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, then the Army muſt and are bound to doe it for them, or elſe they muſt be forced to ſet themſelves in a warlike poſture, and require it of them; which to do, how ſad it would be to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Kingdom, let all judge.</p>
            <p>When any caſe of publike concernment is in debate by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, tending directly to the weale of the people or not, and then referred to a Vote, that Vote carries it right or wrong: Now if the Parliament conſiſt of ſo many ill-affected Members, which was the condition of the Houſe ſince their laſt new moulding, as to carry the Vote to the diſturbance and prejudice of the people, when it is apparently and evidently ſo, and the people ſmart and groane under it, and when they petition no redreſſe can be had, then I beſeech you, what other courſe or meanes is there left for this diſtreſſed people to take, but to uſe the power of an Army? or muſt they and their poſterities, notwithſtanding they were crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted free, lie for ever under ſuch inſupportable languiſhments? It is true, the Army received their Commiſſion from the Parliament, and ſo did the Parliament theirs from the people; ſo that the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my are as equally intruſted by the people, as they are by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or the Parliament by the people: For the Parliament were no Parliament without the peoples leave, nor could they give Commiſſion, till firſt they received one themſelves: whereby it appeares, the Army have their Commiſſions as certainely and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly from the people of England, as any inferiour Officers in Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi>'s Army have theirs from the Parliament; and the people are as really obliged, to ſtand firme and intire to them, whilſt they act according to their Commiſſion, as the Parliament are to countenance and protect any Officer or number of Officers, who refuſe obedience to their Generall, when he commands him or them to betray their truſt. Therefore I ſay, if the Parliament forget their firſt principles, and ſtop their cares from the peoples ſighings, the Army are required (if they violate not the truſt repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in them) to uſe their beſt endeavours to relieve them. And this cleares the third part of their aſſertion, which is the reaſon
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116163:8"/>you give why the Army cannot plead or petition for what they know makes for the right, freedome, peace and ſafety of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and the Kingdome, as they are an Army, to wit,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Becauſe that relates onely to thoſe uſes, for which it was made, limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted within it Commiſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which Commiſſion (as I ſaid before) doth as really authorize them, as an Army, to deſire right from the Parliament for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this Nation, as it did put them in a capacity of fighting, and powring out their blood for their rights; or the Parliaments Commiſſion did inveſt them with power to regulate the affaires of the Kingdome, and conſequently, in caſe of viſible ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, to raiſe and maintaine an Army in otder there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
            <p>If the Parliament declare againſt the Army for the juſt proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and performance of their owne Orders, and Ordinances, they doe as immediately and directly declare againſt themſelves; yea, by ſtriveing to condemne and overthrow the Army, they doe but dig a pit or lay a ſnare (as <hi>David</hi> ſaith) for themſelves to fall into: For if the Parliaments Declarations and Ordinances, by themſelves framed and compoſed, in order to the raiſing and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of a force, and granting them a Commiſſion, were not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Law, which moſt men confeſſe they were, then the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my were culpapble and reſponſible to another Parliament, if any ſhould be after the diſſolution of this, for obeying the Votes and directions of this, yea and this Parliament themſelves could not be free from ſevere examination in this particular. But if the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments Declarations and Ordinances in relation to the levying of an Army, were firmely grounded on Law, and Reaſon, as undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly they were, and ſo kept and preciſely obſerved by the Army; if the Authours of them, viz. the Parliament ſhould begin and perſiſt in the unjuſt violation of them, who is fault-worthy? the Army that keepeth them, or the Parliament who infringe them? If the Parliament command injuſtice, ſhall not they be reſponſible for it, when the Army who did but execute their commands, eſcape Scot-free? Shall the inſtrument be broken, and the hand that made and uſed it, be diſcharged from the fact? Doth the Army crave anie thing but what the Parliament have often promiſed, the Law warrants, your ſelfe, with the reſt of your friends, I hope the Armies friends too, would willingly and gratefully partake of?
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116163:8"/>If they doe, then what is it? If they do not, then why are they ſo much blamed? When the warre was hot in the Kingdome, which, and for which bleſſed for ever be our God, is now aſſwaged and mitigated by the fidelity, valour and unanimity of this Army, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the wiſe conduct of puiſſant <hi>Fairfax,</hi> the onely inſtruments in Gods hands to period our diſmall diſtractions, they never trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the Parliament or themſelves with things of this concernment, but quietly and patiently, as led thereunto by the very hand of providence, obeyed all commands tending to publike ſafety, and freely underwent the ſaddeſt exigences of a fiery Warre: and when none els were honoured with the like victories, they indured without grudging or repineing the teſt and brunt thereof, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver moleſted the Parliament with one ſcrip or line, as other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies did, and at that time well enough reſented too, which might impede them in their publike and ponderous negotiations: yea, they freely ſubjected and expoſed themſelves to the mercileſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities of wind and weather, hunger, nakedneſſe, the diſ-favour and hate of divers of their beſt friends, and what not? But alas! we are now againe in peace, and theſe mercies are utterly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten. Beſides, other Armies before this, did ſeverall times plead and petition, as Armies, not ſo much neceſſitated thereunto, as this Army is, and it was well accepted, and requited with plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble anſwers of ſatisfaction in their juſt demands; yet this Army, if they but offer to petition as an Army, is ſo ill reſented, that they ſhall immediately, without being heard for themſelves, be decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red enemies, &amp;c. Had they but (unworthily) committed thoſe outragious incivilities, and offered ſuch affronts and indignities to the two Houſes of Parliament, as the London Faction (the beſt friends to the impeached Members) did, I dare affirme, the City and whole Kingdome had been flameing about their eares ere this day: but this is not ſo conſiderable a crime in them, nay, no crime at all, as ſome peremptorily report, becauſe they were no Army, had they but a Commiſſion, then this were a fault in them, but as the caſe ſtands now, it is none. Had not our Brethren the Scots (not to deprive them of their dues, which they deſerved) all that they deſired or demanded as an Army?<note place="margin">Pax quaeritur Bellc. <hi>L.G. Crumwells</hi> Mot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</note> But now <hi>tempora mutan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur &amp; nos mutamur in illis,</hi> this Army muſt not deſire thoſe things as an Army, which other Armies with much facility have obtained: and all the reaſon I know for it is, becauſe peace is extracted from
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116163:9"/>warre, by the prodigall effuſion of the precious blood of divers in this Army.</p>
            <p>In the next place, you ſay, <hi>for their affirming they are not a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenarie Army,</hi> you will not ſpend time to diſpute it, and in my judgement you have taken the wiſeſt courſe, unleſſe you be ſo good a Sophiſter, as to make truth appeare falſhood, and falſhood truth; which is ſomething difficult in the apprehenſion of any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man. Yet, ſay you, every one ſees they inſiſt much on their wages: and good reaſon they ſhould, when ſo many of them have ſpent the prime and flower of their yeares in the ſervice of the Kingdome, divers of them being men of trades and callings, and have charges of families, who depend wholly upon their honeſt endeavours, and were able ſufficiently to maintaine them before this warre, and now have no ſubſiſtence or livelihood, whereby to relieve themſelves or families, but that ſmall pittance of pay they ſeldome, yet ſometimes receive from the State, who called them from their functions to publike imployments.</p>
            <p>Others there be, who though they have ſufficient eſtates, yet ſome of them have been wholly ſequeſtred in thoſe parts of the Kingdome where the King had any Garriſons, or parties to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them. And the reſt by reaſon of the unſupportable taxes of the Kingdome, had little or no benefit by them: yea I have known ſome that have ſerved the Parliament faithfully and valiantly, who have been worſe dealt with in their eſtates then Papiſts, and others who were in actuall ſervice againſt them. And now tell me, if the Parliament are not bound to give the labourer his deſerved hire, and this Army have not ſufficient cauſe to inſiſt on their wages: I am very confident, that if the Parliament had but allowed them what was promiſed, and for the uſe levied in the Kingdome, you nor they ſhould have heard one word more of them, in relation to that particular.</p>
            <p>And for that Scripture you alledge in the 3. of <hi>Luke</hi> 14. that Souldiers ſhould be content with their wages, the Army have been in the whole progreſſe of this warre ſo farre from grudging, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineing, or being diſcontent with their wages, that they have been very well content without it, even to the admiration of all the Countreyes they have marched thorow, and (for ought they or I can perceive) are like ſo to continue yet a while. The Kingdome are ſenſible enough of nineteen millions of money (ſome ſay
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116163:9"/>73000000.) that hath been with more then ordinary haſt, and in little time extracted from them, and if any part of it be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported beyond Seas, it's paſt their skill to bring it backe againe: yea they know alſo, the Army have not received above 1400000. l. of all that vaſt ſum: and how the reſidue is diſpoſed of, cannot (I thinke) be well and honeſtly accounted. I preſume, that if all the Parliament-men in England, Committee-men, Sequeſtrators, Excize-men and all the Aſſembly-men, with all their Clarks, Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, and fellowes, and all other ſuch Officers made ſince the War in pay, were but drawne together into one field, you ſhould find them in number to ſuper-equallize half Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi>'s Army, and theſe men have been conſtantly payed, <hi>de die in diem,</hi> from day to day; but the Army who have ſecured theſe by the frequent diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of their blood, muſt be content with a twelve moneths pay in two years time, and Ordinances muſt be made for the diſcharge of their quarters too, of purpoſe to ſet the Countrey and them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the ears, by making them believe the ſouldiers muſt do what is impoſſible for them to do, <hi>viz.</hi> diſcharge their quarters, when they have ſcarce money to buy them cloathes to keep them from the cold wind, and aire.</p>
            <p>Truly Sir, you might rather admire the patience of the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that they have forborne ſo long, and been no more earneſt for their wages, then that they have inſiſted ſo much thereon at this time. There be divers Sequeſtrators and others, who inrich themſelves with the ruines of honeſter men, and fill their coffers with the decayed Countreyes wealth; yet ſuch men may eſcape unqueſtioned, for their oppreſſion and injuſtice, when the Army ſhall be reviled, deſpiſed, declared againſt for inſiſting on their wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and petitioning for it, though in a legall way: but the old Proverb is verified by this, <hi>That ſome had better ſteale a horſe, then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſtand and looke on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is the high and mighty Sequeſtrator of Suffolke, his name is <hi>Baſe,</hi> (ſo is his nature) and if his head had been ſequeſtred from his body long ſince, it had been better for thoſe parts: his owne eſtate at the beginning of this warre was worth 70. or 80. l. <hi>per annum,</hi> and as much in debt as his eſtate was worth; yet in theſe few yeares of Englands miſery, hath he been making his harveſt; for he hath not onely diſcharged his debt, but proffered to a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, an acquaintance of mine in that Countrey, above 3000. l.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116163:10"/>for his houſe and Land that he lived on; and (as I am credibly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed) hath purchaſed ſome ſtore of Land in the ſame Countrey, and alſo ſent ſome quantity of Caſh into Holland againſt a rainy day, there to keep Chriſtmas with his Grandſire <hi>Waller,</hi> and the reſt of that rabble, birds of a feather, flock together: and therefore you may imagine <hi>ex pede Herculem,</hi> by the dimenſion of the foote, the proportion of the whole body. So much for that part of your Examination: then you continue thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For what you ſpeake of the Arbitrary Power of a State, and of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, oppreſſion, particular Parties and Intereſts, if you apply it to the preſent caſe, to juſtifie your not obeying the Parliament, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it ſignifies nothing, then I muſt ſay, it is exceeding unjuſt when you do not inſtance in any one action wherein they are willingly guilty of any ſuch charge.</hi> To this I ſhall reply as conciſe an anſwer, as I can, and that in theſe enſuing particulars:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That you have miſtaken the candid meaning of the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for it ſpeakes not poſitively of the Parliament, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that they have done violence, oppreſſion, injuſtice, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whereas the Declaration ſaith, they will vindicate the juſt power and rights of this Kingdome in Parliament, againſt all ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary power, violence, &amp;c. it ſpeaketh not in relation to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, as I ſaid before, unleſſe your and their conſciences informe you, that they, or rather ſome of their Members, are guilty of the premiſes, and ſo come under the laſh of that Declaration; but thoſe, whatever hee or they bee, who have, doe or ſhall for the future practice arbitrarineſſe, violence, oppreſſion, &amp;c. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the free People of England, as the impeached Members have done.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is not wiſdome in any man, or ſociety of men, to inſtance particulars, before a generall is propoſed, though but in the charge of a ſingle man.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If all were true that you ſay, and that it were ſo, that if the Army apply not what they ſpeake of arbitrary powers, violence, oppreſſion, &amp;c. to the preſent caſe, it ſignifies nothing, and that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is unjuſt in the Army, that they doe not inſtance one action of injuſtice the Parliament have done, yet it can be reputed (time, place, and other inconveniences conſidered) no leſſe then a point of greateſt modeſty, meekneſſe, and wiſdom in them to forbeare a while.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:116163:10"/>
            <p n="5">5. Though your miſapprehenſion were granted for a truth, which I dare not doe, that it was the intent of the Declaration peremptorily and poſitively, to tax the Parliament of arbitrarineſſe, violence oppreſſion, &amp;c. yet for your ſatisſaction, and the Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Army from that aſperſion of Injuſtice you eaſt on it, I ſhall inſtance in ſome particulars, wherein arbitrarineſſe, vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, oppreſſion, &amp;c. hath been conmitted in a more then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary meaſure, and with unaccuſtomed ſpeed, though I confeſſe, it is ſuch a point, that I had rather deny my ſelfe in ſilence, and weep over the failings of men, then to rip them open to the view of the world.</p>
            <p>One is the late ordering of the <hi>Militia</hi> of London, and remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving it out of the hands of thoſe who had (during the late Warres) ſerved the Parliament and Kingdome faithfully and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liantly, not fearing to hang their lives on the points of their ſwords (as at Gloceſter and both Newbery fights) in defence of the juſt Freedomes and Rights of this Nation, and diſpoſing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of into the hands of ſome, who are no leſſe then Delinquents, if they had their due, and others whoſe cowardly hearts dare not adventure further then they ſee the ſmoke of London Chimneyes, and yet are (forſooth) tied to a Sword in a Militia poſture; ſome againe there be who have all theſe times kept at a diſtance and ſtood as Newterall and diſ-affected to both parties, and theſe are the men to whom is committed not only the guard of that renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, famous, wealthy, and populous City of London, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of the whole Kingdome, the Army once disbanded, it being the Head-Quarters and Magazine thereof; but they are alſo intruſted with the ſafety of the Parliament, the grand Court of the Kingdome, and thoſe honeſt conſcientious Worthies of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don were diſmiſt, to their extreme diſhonour, in the vulgars view, as if they had done ſomething worthy caſhiering, and that, upon no grounds in the earth, nor as much as one word was objected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. If they may do thus to the City, that is as an intire, compact Army within it ſelfe, what will they not do to the whole Kingdome? Would they not have intruſted Malignants and ill-affected perſons with the <hi>Militia</hi> thereof as at London, and ſo ſet the Kingdome all on ſire againe? Was not this the ready way un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it? But it is evident to all men, that what was done in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, was in order to a plot of inſlaving the free-born people
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116163:11"/>of England, and that chiefly by the traiterous impeached Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, who well knew that the fore-mentioned honeſt party were not perfidious enough to ſerve their deſignes, and rather then they would want help to ſet them forward, would intruſt any, though never ſo bad, therefore moved the Houſe therewith, and by their ſubtill inſtigations and malevolent influences on divers Members, got this curſed conſpiracy paſſed and ordered, to the great diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of all the honeſt ſincere party of the City, and indan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering the ruine of this enough miſerable Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Againe, the unjuſt impriſonment of Lievtenant-Colonell <hi>John Lilburne</hi> without expreſſing the cauſe of his commitment in the Warrant, though by due courſe of Law they ought and are bound thereunto: and keeping him under miſerable reſtraint, not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting him to have the uſe of ink and paper, nor ſuffering his wife or any of his friends to come neare him for a long time.</p>
            <p>Then the breaking open M. <hi>Overtons</hi> doore of his houſe, that ſtout ſtickler for Englands Liberties, by a company of<note n="*" place="margin">Pro. 29.12.</note> uncivill Ruffians, and ſurpriſing him and his wife in bed, and forcing him thence to appeare before the Houſe of Lords, without Order or Warrant that he could at that time heare of, though much deſired, but after they pretended a Warrant from the Lords, from thence they dragged him head long through the ſtreets, through dirt and mire, and on the ſtones, all the way moſt vilely abuſed and beaten to Newgate, and there laid in double Irons, where he hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued from the third of November, 1646. till this preſent time, and no kind of reliefe or hearing can be had for this miſerable and diſtreſſed man: Bur further, as not content with this, and not ſuppoſing it woe enough for the poore man, they ſend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to his houſe, where finding his ſad-hearted wife and three ſmall children about her, (poore ſoule diſconſolate enough God knowes) tooke her and his brother away, and forced them to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare at the Lords Barre, plundered and ranſacked his houſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the helpleſſe children to the mercy of the wide ſtreets, and all this before any preſentment or due proceſſe of Law procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: and from the Houſe of Lords, both of them were ſent to the new Priſon in Maiden-Lane, where he ſtill continues, but ſhe under pretence of another Order was dragged in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that her husband was, to infamous Bridewell through dirt and mire, with an Infant of halfe a yeare old in her armes, not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:116163:11"/>regarding her Sex, Age or preſent condition,<note place="margin">Vir &amp; ux<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r ſune quaſi unica per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſona, qula care una, &amp; ſanguis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> but abuſing her with the nick-names of Whore, Strumpet, &amp;c. where ſhe hath been e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince kept in miſerable reſtraint, not permitting her to have the liberty of being impriſoned with her husband, notwithſtanding Gods Command againſt ſuch ſeparation, or as much as once to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit him in all this time, or enjoy the comfort of her children a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout her, or ſuffering her to go a little abroad with her Keeper, to take the freſh ayre, though her life hath been apparently indan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered by the want thereof.</p>
            <p>Then there was Major <hi>Balſum,</hi> who had ſerved the Parliament conſcientiouſly and ſtoutly, under the command of Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> he was a long time (after the diſſolution of that Army) a humble Petitioner to the Parliament for ſome part of his Arrears, having nought elſe to depend on for the maintenance of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, his wife and three or foure children, but he waited ſo long, and to ſo little purpoſe, (as moſt doe who wait there) till at laſt he died moſt miſerably for want of ordinary ſuſtenance: and when he was dead, his* Father-in-Law and wife,<note place="margin">M. Michell.</note> knew not how to bury him in foure or five daies, for want of money, till at laſt ſome mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney was ordered his wife, wherewith ſhe buried him.</p>
            <p>There were thirteen or fourteen more ſouldiers that ſerved in the ſame Army, who were ſtarved in the ſame manner,<note place="margin">Pro. 21.7.22.16.</note> which will be proved upon oath; <hi>the robbery of the wicked ſhall deſtroy them, becauſe they refuſe to doe judgement. He that oppreſſeth the poore to increaſe his riches, and he that giveth unto the rich, ſhall ſurely want.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 2.3, 5.</note> 
               <hi>And I will come neere to you to judgement, and I will be a ſwift wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt the Sorcerers, and againſt the Adulterers, and againſt falſe ſwearers, and againſt thoſe that oppreſſe the hireling in his wages, the widdow and the fatherleſſe, and that turne away the ſtranger from his right, and fear not me, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, the Widdowes and Orphans of thoſe ſlaine in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Parliament, who were well maintained by their hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, and fathers, before this warre, are now faine to beg their bread from doore to doore in London and elſewhere, for want of promiſed relief from the Parliament.</p>
            <p>Beſides, their refuſing to heare and anſwer the cries, groanes and Petitions of the diſtreſſed, and thoſe who intruſted them to ſit, though bound thereunto by the ſtricteſt ingagements of the Laws
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116163:12"/>of England, of Conſcience, and Reaſon, which way of Petition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is one of the greateſt priviledges the people of this Kingdome are inveſted with, yet often refuſed, as that of the vertuous Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman Mrs. <hi>Lilburne,</hi> preſented to every Member of the Houſe, as they went in but never any ſatisfactory anſwer returned,<note place="margin">The foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges relate on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to particular men, but they have ſpeciall influence on the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</note> as if they were reſolved to make that honeſt conſcientious Gentleman, and gallant Souldier for his Countreyes rights, her husband, a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall ſlave.</p>
            <p>Then the Petition of the entire Counties of Hereford and Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kingham, though juſt, legall and ſeaſonable, was caſt aſide, reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and at laſt diſgracefully burnt by the hands of the Common-Hangman. If they will diſappoint two whole Counties in their reaſonable demands, ſure a si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gle man ſhall ſcarce have audience, or right from them.</p>
            <p>Alſo the Petition of the Army, which contained nothing but what was equitable, and honeſt, yet before it was preſented, whilſt the Army were but deſiring their Generall to ſolicit for them in behalfe thereof, they were declared enemies to the State, and obſtructers of the reliefe of Ireland, if they perſiſted: as if their being an Army and fighting for freedome, had deprived them of their freedomes and birth-rights.</p>
            <p>Another maine and more generall oppreſſion, is the billeting of Souldiers on the enough waſted Countrey upon Free-quarter, the heavieſt preſſure they undergo for the time, and neither giving them their due pay, that ſo they might be able to diſcharge their quarters, nor abateing it in the Taxes and Contributions of the Countrey, which are daily continued.</p>
            <p>I ſhall forbeare to proceed any further in the ſad relation of theſe paſſages, they are already ſo common in each mans mouth: I ſhall onely requeſt you to peruſe the Petition of the inſlaved Commons of England,<note place="margin">Iuly 6. 1647.</note> called <hi>Englands dolefull lamentation,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to his Excellency Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> and there you may behold acts enough of arbitrarineſſe, violence, and oppreſſion, and if theſe things be not done by the knowledge or conſent of ſome Members of Parliament, why then is not eaſe, deliverance and redreſſe given, and the juſt Lawes of the Kingdome ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and duly executed after ſo many Petitions preſented? Is it poſſible that all theſe and many more acts (which I ſhall forbeare
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116163:12"/>to repeat) of arbitrarineſſe, violence and oppreſſion, can be done by any but by them, or if they be done by others, (their inſtruments) it muſt needs be by their conſent, and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing of them therein, they durſt as well run their heads in the fire, and there let them conſume to aſhes, as once offer to practice any of the premiſes contained in the ſaid Petition, without ſpeciall favour of ſome of the great Councell of the Land. Therefore do you weigh and conſider impartially theſe things, and tell me if there be not a fault, and that a horrible one in that high Court of Judicature. And truly, I can ſee no way how it may be prevented, whilſt they ſuffer ſo many<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 3.4. Eccl. 10.16.</note> Boyes, (who know better how to Court Ladies then create Lawes) Commiſſion of Array-men, men whoſe eſtates were but lately (and are ſtill for ought I know) under Sequeſtration for Delinquency, to reſide, ſit, vote, and act amongſt them.</p>
            <p>I ſhall inſiſt no longer on this, but proceed to the next thing obſervable in this part of your Examination, where you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme for truth, that which (in my judgement) is a groſſe miſtake.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That thoſe who have a Legiſlative power, have not altogether a limited power; but that is no more in this (ſay you) then in all Parliaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This I utterly deny, and doe contrarily affirme, that thoſe who have power to make Lawes in England, have ſeverall bounds and limits, which by no meanes they are to exceed; one is this.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Freedome and Birth-rights of the people is one main limit; for it is not with us as with other Nations, we are not under that vaſſallage and thraledome the Turks or French are, if that were our condition, then indeed <hi>Stat pro ratione vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas,</hi> they were as limitles, as thoſe States be, and may impoſe what they pleaſe upon us, and make their curſed wills the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples cruell Law: but (praiſed be God) that is not the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Kingdome yet, though twice deſigned to be ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to ſlavery within theſe halfe dozen yeares; wee are yet Free-men and not left to the limitleſſe diſpoſing of an arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry State: this therefore is one cord which binds a Legiſlative power in this Kingdom, from impoſing and laying what loads they pleaſe on the free people thereof.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The peoples knowledge of their owne Liberties, is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:116163:13"/>great hinderance to this limitleſſe power, it is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely, (if the Parliament continue their extraordinary taxes, and preſſures on the Countrey, after the disbanding of this Army, and uſe ſuch violence againſt the Commons of England as they have done by their Committees, and other unjuſt Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and not hear and anſwer the Petitions of the afflicted) but that they will be all ready with their clubs, &amp; other weapons on their ſhoulders, to ſtand upon their own guards. But I hope, they ſhall have no cauſe for it, &amp; that the Parliament of England will not take ſuch a boundleſſe power unto themſelves, as you would make them and us believe is their due.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Right reaſon, which in caſes conducing to this end, hath no better Judge then the ſenſible computation of the vulgar, and this is a great ſtop and obſtruction to that limitleſſe Legiſlative power, for nothing that exceeds the confines of right reaſon, according to common acceptation in caſes of this nature, may or ought be preſſed on a free Nation; if they do, the impoſers are both liable to anſwer them, &amp; like to bear them themſelves. <hi>Non ſolùm quod licet, ſed quid eſt conveniens eſt conſiderandum, nihil quod eſt inconveniens eſt licitum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Scripture, with which right reaſon accords, &amp; which is as ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, full &amp; ample, for regulation and government of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man,<note place="margin">Am. 2.4, 6, 7. &amp; 1.11.</note> as the inward, and therfore binds and limits all Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlative powers in this Kingdom, to compoſe, conſtitute &amp; enact Laws expreſly according thereunto. Therefore theſe things ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly weighed in the juſt ſcales of indifferent judgments, do (to me) clearly prove, that there is undoubtedly a reſtriction of Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative powers: yet I ſhal freely lay down my own, and ſubmit to ſounder judgments, when the contrary to this that is ſpoken, is made apparent. The next thing conſiderable in this part of your Examination, is this: <hi>And that ſo long as the calamities of the times did neceſſitate Armies, there muſt needs be burdens laid, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to more then ordinary preſſures;</hi> but was that the Parliaments fault, or thoſe that did oppoſe them?</p>
            <p>Here is another miſtake, that you go about to vindicate the Parliament from that which the Army never intended to charge them with: it is acknowledged by all men, that in caſes of more then ordinary need, the people muſt be neceſſitated to undergo extraordinary preſſures; neither is the blame laid altogether on the Parliament, but moſtly on thoſe, who (contrarie to Law) conſtrained them thereunto.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:116163:13"/>
            <p>In the next place you propound this Quaere: <hi>And that theſe preſſures and burdens muſt be ſtill kept upon the people, is it the fault of the Parliament, or the Army that will not disband?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is already made manifeſt by what precedes, that it is neither the fault of the Army, that they are not disbanded, or the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey oppreſſed. For, it is not in the power of the Army to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs or burden the Countrey, though they would do it, unleſſe the Parliament inſtate them into it, or inforce them to ſuch exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, that they are neceſſitated thereunto; for if they ſhould, the whole Kingdome (to whom they are but an inconſiderable party) would quickly oppoſe and deſtroy them: but they well know the fault is not in the Army, which makes them ſo apt on all occaſions to ſide with them in thoſe things that are juſt. And let all men judge, whoſe fault is it, the Army will not disband, or the Countrey are oppreſt? the Parliaments or the Armies? when they neither bring (after ſeven years ſitting) Liberty or Freedome to this free-born Nation, (nothing in the world, but their own wils obſtructing them) or give the Army any lawfull, honeſt, or reaſonable encouragements to disband, but contrarily have uſed all means tending to the mutinous and diſhonourable disbanding thereof, as by faire proffers to divide the Officers from their Souldiers, &amp; the Souldiers from their Officers, &amp; when that could not take expected effect, then to divide the whole Army from the Countrey, and the Countrey from them,<note place="margin">This was done when the Head-quarters were at Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron Walden.</note> witneſs that Petition framed by ſome Members of Parliament and fent into Eſſex to get hands to it, and then preſent it to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment again. Again, they declared againſt that Petition, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be preſented them from the Army, without hearing them plead for themſelves, wherein they deſired nothing but the auditing of their Accounts, their Debenters to bee caſt up,<note place="margin">Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my at the Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devous nigh. Royſton.</note> ſome ſatisfaction for Arrears in hand, ſecurity for the reſt, and an Act of Indempnity, not as their Votes import, where they ſay, that an Act of Indempnity ſhall be made for the wrongs, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, miſdemeanours, &amp;c. of the Army, for if the Armies defence of the Parliaments Cauſe have relation to any ſuch Acts the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome may thank the Parliament and require ſatisfaction from them, for put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſwords in their hands, but or things done in the juſt proſecution of theirs and the kingdomes ſervice: alſo proviſion to be made for the reliefe of the widdowes and children of thoſe sluine in the States ſervice, and for marmed ſouldiers; yea they were ſo exceeding imperious and high in this particular, as if they had been abſolute Monarchs, and intended no leſs then the utter ruin &amp; overthrow of this ſo gallant &amp; powerfull an Army, for providing for their own ſecurities, defending the peoples Liberties and Priviledges againſt their predominant incroachments</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:116163:14"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:116163:14"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:116163:15"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:116163:15"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:116163:16"/>
            <p>Moreover, becauſe you would have the Kingdome take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that the reaſon of their burdens and oppreſſions is becauſe the Army will not disband, if they had disbanded at that time and upon thoſe tearmes, (whileſt perſiſting in their juſt Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) how deplorable the Kings, Kingdoms and their State had been, the ſhalloweſt capacity can eaſily determine. Had they not been given over to the arbitrary, mercileſſe power of their malicious adverſaries, (the impeached Members) whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes on the Army and Kingdome were immediately effected after the diſſipation of this Army? Was not this the opening of a faire gap thereunto? Would not the Authours of that illegall Declaration have ſeized on the perſons of every one in the Army, after disbanding, where ever they found them, and have hanged them up one by one, the juſt deſert of the States enemies, as that unjuſt Declaration would make them? Doth not their Covenant bind them to this, the Army being (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) declared enemies? and if they ſhould attempt to plead for themſelves, there is no way left, they are declared obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of the reliefe of Ireland, notwithſtanding his Excellency was then ordering a party for that ſervice upon the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments owne tearmes, and enemies to the peace of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, though from the beginning the Army freely adventured their lives for to obtaine a ſafe peace for it, yea and that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration remaine and ſtill would have been uncancelled on Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, had not they (with the bleſſing of God) prevented it; and who once durſt ſpeak a word in their behalf, or expoſtulate the caſe for them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But happily you will object, that the Parliament did proffer the Army an Act of Indempnity, by which they were ſecured from that Declaration, that it could lay no hold on them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. To this I anſwer: firſt, That Act of indempnity was onely for the wrongs, oppreſſions, and miſdemeanours, &amp;c. committed by the Army, <hi>in tempore &amp; loco Belli,</hi> in time and place of Warre, whereof, as I ſaid before, they were not guilty, unleſſe the ſincere proſecution of their ſervice be wrong, oppreſſion, miſdemeanour, &amp;c. and therefore that Act cannot ſecure them from this Declaration.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:116163:16"/>
            <p n="2">2. Againe, the Army Petition, and their perſiſting in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation thereof, was not in the time of warre, but after the diſſolution and diſſipation of the <hi>Kings</hi> party, and reducing his Garriſons; therefore that Act of Indempnity, which was onely intended for things done <hi>in tempore, &amp; loco belli,</hi> in time and place of Warre, cannot ſecure them from that Declaration, for perſiſting in their Petition, which was done <hi>ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in tempore ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> loco belli,</hi> neither in time, or place of Warre, but in times of Peace.</p>
            <p>Therefore (I ſay) theſe things well conſidered, in a judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous breſt, there is but little ſound reaſon (that I know of) why the Kingdom ſhould either imagine, the Armies not disbanding, is the cauſe of their burdens, and preſſure, or the Army ſhould disband on ſuch ſlight and unſafe termes, eſpecially the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments own principle <hi>(viz.)</hi> that obedience binds not men to cut their own throates, giving them ſufficient encouragement, to make better tearmes for themſelves, the King, and Kingdom. And now I ſhall proceed to the next thing laid down by you; which is briefly this.</p>
            <p>That the Parliament have judged the forces raiſed by the <hi>King,</hi> were to invade the peoples rights and liberties, and the juſt power, and rights of this Kingdome in Parliament, and did publiſh the ſame in their Declarations, and thereupon did raiſe both this and ſeverall other Armies, to oppoſe and reſiſt thoſe forces: but (ſay you) how theſe Declarations give them a right to judge, what theſe liberties, juſt power or rights are, either of the Parliament, or people, is (I think) paſt all humane underſtanding to conceive, neither the lawes of God, nor the lawes of the Kingdom having made them Judges, nor having put any of the weights or meaſures of Juſtice, in the behalfe of others into their hands.</p>
            <p>It is not denyed but the Parliament did judge (as by right to them it belonged) that the forces raiſed by the King were to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade the liberties of the people, and that they publiſhed the ſame in their Declarations, and raiſed both this and ſeverall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Armies for the prevention thereof, and preſervation of the people.</p>
            <p>But here againe is the Army miſapprehended by you, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:116163:17"/>up, before they are downe, they go not about to draw any concluſion of that nature (nor can you have any grounds for ſuch ſlight ſurmiſes from their expreſſions, or actions) as to the matter of being Judges of liberty and freedome, from the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aments Declarations, although that in it ſelfe, be a caſe <hi>dubious,</hi> and (therefore) diſputable enough, for if they muſt not know, and conſequently judge of liberty and freedome, how muſt or dare they fight (which you well approve of) for them, unleſſe they fight, for they know not what, or make uſe of an implicite faith, and believe all the Parliament ſay to be true, as men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, which to the underſtanding of any reaſonable capacity, is but a rotten, trayle, and unſound foundation for them to build on) but the Parliament themſelves have judged of their owne priviledges, and the liberties of the whole Kingdome, and have ſeverall times declared what they are, and that when the people are grieved, or oppreſt, they ſhould immediately repaire to them, by way of Petition and redreſſe, ſhould be forthwith granted; this is one of the greateſt priviledges of the free peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this Kingdome, have according to <hi>Magna Charta, Pet.</hi> of <hi>Right,</hi> and their own many and frequent Declarations, but alas! how hath this been perfideouſly perverted? (as if there were not the leaſt knowledge, or feare of God amongſt men) and the people (under a faire coloured pretence of peace, and freedom) altogether ſubjugated to warre, vaſſalage and thraldome, (had not the wiſdom and power of God prevented it) this appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the late commotions occaſioned by ſome Members of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and their unjuſt refuſall of ſeverall legall Petitions pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cented unto them, which (notwithſtanding the Lawes of the Kingdome, and their own Declarations to the contrary) were rejected; yea, and with the greateſt infamy, and ſhame that could be, conſumed with fire in ſeverall parts of <hi>London,</hi> by the hands of the common Hangman, ſo inſolently and proudly have ſome of them behaved themſelves towards the free people of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore (I ſay) if the Parliament ſhall declare to the whole Kingdome, what their immunites, rights and freedoms are, and alſo, what of due belongs to thmeſelves, whilſt ſitting in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116163:17"/>and then ſhall goe about (under the painted ſhew of breach of priviledge) to anticipate, and ſubvert the antient pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of the people of <hi>England;</hi> muſt not the Army, (who were raiſed by the Kingdome for their defence) as in the ſtricteſt bonds, of duty and conſcience, they are obliged, once open their lips, to crave and begg, for the people their proper rights, but they muſt (in an infamous manner) be tearmed Judges? And now Sir I appeale to your ſelfe, if the Army ever went about to determine any cauſes in the Kingdome, except what they did by the Parliaments permiſſion, with their Swords, againſt the publike enemy, onely they have repreſented their owne, and the peoples often rejected grievances to them, by way of hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Petition; and if this be a contracting power or right, from the Parliaments Declarations, of being Judges of their own, and the peoples liberties, powers, and rights, let the world judge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them and you.</p>
            <p>For that you ſay, the Army can onely do (what your erring fancy hath ſuggeſted to you) by the length of their Swords, which can be no good Standard, for it will be lyable to alteration, when a longer Sword comes: I ſay their Swords are ſo long, and ſo good a Standard, that it never yet, (I know not what it may do) met with a longer, to remove, or alter it, from proſecution, (with zeale to Gods glory, and the Kingdome benefit) the righteous cauſe, they have in the ſincerity of their hearts undertaken, in behalfe of the King, Parliament, and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Then you proceed thus.</p>
            <p>And when the people of this Kingdome, have underſtood, and conſidered this, it is not likely, they will leave the ſetled courſe of Law, and Juſtice, in the knowne Courts of the Kingdome, to be judged by any one who can raiſe the greateſt tumult.</p>
            <p>Indeed now you have paid the Army to ſome purpoſe, if the people were ſurpriſed with ſuch a ſpirit of deluſion, as to believe the deviating dictates of your thoughts; and now I deſire you or any of your Competitioners to demonſtrate, in any one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular (or confeſſe you injure them) wherein this Army have taken upon them, the place or authority of Judges, or hindered the people, from following the ſetled courſe of Law and Juſtice in the known Courts of the Kingdome, Or that his Excellency
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:116163:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:116163:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:116163:19"/>Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> at whom you chiefly aime, ever inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or offered to judge any thing, but what the Parliament have determined already, unleſſe thoſe things which conduce to the weale of his Army, the very terrour of <hi>Englands</hi> enemies, and all other Souldiers in <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> which in duty, and conſcience he is bound to do.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſpeak of a tumult, by which you meane this Army, or otherwiſe you overthrow the reſt of your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, you do the Parliament themſelves more wrong and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, under the ſpecious pretence of a friend, in one word, then ever the Army did, or durſt, though they could do them, in their whole life time, nay, as much as the Kings party have ever done, in expreſſion, ſince the warre began; For if the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my be a Tumult, they were raiſed by the Parliament, whereby it appeares, you make them, whom you ſe ſtrive to defend the Authours of this Tumult.</p>
            <p>Which muſt needes follow ſay you, if they, meaning the Kingdome, allow this Army, ſuppoſe it 14000. men to be Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es now, then any 150000. in the Kingdome may judge the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and a greater number then <hi>ad infinitum;</hi> by which it doth appeare, that the Army making themſelves Judges in theſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, doth overthrow and take away the Ordinance of God, and Magiſtracy; then which amongſt men, I cannot imagine what is a greater impiety.</p>
            <p>Truly Sir, I know no greater impiety amongſt men, tending to publike harme and prejudice, then to miſapprehend the ſerene and candid thoughts of others, if what preceeds this conſequence of yours had been true, as appeares it is not, then this would have held good; for it is a certaine maxime, that if 14000. men, in a tumultuous way, be Judges now, then any 150000. men, in the Kingdome, may judge the Army, and a greater number them <hi>ad infinitum.</hi> But your miſapplication of this concluſion, is the ſpoyle of it; had you but turned this from the Innocent, and layd it on the guilty, I meane the impeached Members, then <hi>rem acu tetigoras,</hi> you had laid the ſaddle on the right horſe, and if that courſe of theirs, were not directly to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow the Ordinance of God, and Magiſtracy, when they went about to judge, without the leaſt pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> or ſhew in the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:116163:19"/>earth for it, or reaſon given, not onely the Army, but the whole Kingdome, with a company of rude deboiſt Reformadoes, who better know, how to raiſe mutinies, ſweare, damne, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineere, and make black pots ſalute each others crownes, then to do their Countrey any true and faithfull ſervice in the field, then will I forfeit my judgment utterly; for they were ſuch good friends to Magiſtracy, that by their unparalleld barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous behaviour, they forced the Speakers of both Houſes, and the reſt of the honeſt Members to flye for liberty, if not for life and make this Army their chiefe refuge, and all becauſe they judged it meet: They armed, and diſarmed whom they pleaſed in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> killed one or two, whoſe lives were worth many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of theirs, manned their workes, planted their Ordinance againſt the Parliament themſelves, then conſtrained to reſide with the Army, and this alſo was becauſe they judged it fit. Had this Army done theſe, or the like incomparable actions againſt the Parliament and Kingdome, then might you have ſafely ſaid, that they overthrew both the Ordinance of God and Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, then which amongſt men, I know not a greater impiety. And therefore now ſee, if this Army, whom you would make the Kingdome believe, would be their Judges, to make them more odious in the eyes of the ſoone deceived vulgar, had not inſtead of being Judges, ſtuck firme and intire to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and againe interpoſed their lives and fortunes betwixt them and the face of danger, and that in the very pinch and nick of hazard, and put thoſe grand Judges of <hi>England,</hi> into their own proper places againe, with honour and ſafety, what Judges ſhould we have had, but a company of impeached Traytors, with their rivalls, who better deſerve a three legg'd ſtoole to hang on, then ſeates in the Parliament houſe to ſit on. and any longer to diſturbe the Kingdom, by their helliſh plots, and practices; and if this be ſuch an impiety as you would have us imagine it to be, then let any impartiall man in <hi>England</hi> judge.</p>
            <p>But not to ſtay any longer here, let us proceed to the next part of your examination; which you ſay down thus.</p>
            <p>Beſides their refuſing to obey the Parliament, under whoſe Command they are, or ought to be, is againſt many particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:116163:20"/>precepts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.10, <hi>Jud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 8.11.</note> and directions in the word of God, as you may find them laid downe in the Margent.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To this I anſwer firſt, that they never refuſed obedience to the Parliament in any thing, except when they commanded them to deſtroy themſelves, through the prevalency of a wicked and ſiniſter party in the Houſe, and then they did no more then what the Parliaments own Principles led them unto, as is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy plainely manifeſted.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the Scriptures you alledge, I ſhall i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſiſt on the firſt onely, as the full ſcope, and ſubſtance of all the other; the words are theſe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.</note> Let every ſoule be ſubject to the higher Powers for there is no power, but of God; the powers that be are ordained of God. This Text of Scripture to them who rightly underſtand it, makes nothing at all for you, as ſhall appeare hereafter, this power the Apoſtle ſpeakes of in this place, (with which the Law of this Kingdom and the Parliaments own forecited Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, do admirably, and truly concurre) is not meant the Perſons, or perſonall commands of any, but the juſt eſtabliſhed lawes of a Kingdome to which obedience, active, or paſſive muſt be given; for this power, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o me the Apoſtle ſeemes to diſpute it himſelfe the better to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t it ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of controverſie, is that which is placed originally,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dec. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>un.</hi> 14.1647. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.</note> and fundamentally, according to that wiſe obſervation of the Armies, in the Office, and but Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterially in the perſons; obſerve both the firſt, and ſecond verſes, and you ſhall finde the Apoſtle ſaith nothing of perſons as if he did not meane them at all in that place, onely enioynes all to yeeld obedience,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 3.</note> and ſubiection to the higher powers which is the Law of a Kingdome; and in the next verſe he ſpeakes of the Adminiſtration of that higher power in theſe words, for Rulers are not a terrour to good workes, but to the evill;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 4.</note> and in the following verſe he ſaith, for he is the Miniſter of God to thee for good, but if thou do that which is evill, be afraid, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But thirdly, the Apoſtles expreſſion hath an univerſall extent, and there is never a rationall living ſoule under the Sun, exempted therefrom, from the Prince, to the pooreſt man that ſits on the threſhold, but every ſoule muſt, if they diſobey not this injunction, be ſubject to the higher powers: which pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:116163:20"/>as is manifeſt, are not the pleaſures, or wills of great men (becauſe they themſelves are not acquitted from ſubjection to the higher powers) but of the eſtabliſhed well grounded Law of a Kingdome, by generall conſent, and for this cauſe is that infallible Gramaticall Rule, <hi>nemo ſibi imperare po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt,</hi> which is the reaſon Schoolemen cannot frame a <hi>prima perſona imperativi modi,</hi> for indeed, who is it that can command himſelfe? and if no man, how can a Prince be ſubject to the higher powers, he being the higheſt power himſelfe, when he cannot command himſelfe? unleſſe you will allow with me, that the Law is the higheſt power, and he is under the Command thereof as well as the meaneſt: ſo that it appeares, if the Prince be not ſubject to the Law of the Kingdom, as well as others, the Apoſtles words (which are expreſly that every Soule, that is, man, woman, and Child, to their abilities, muſt be ſubject to the higher powers, that is the Law whereunto all men are confined, are ſpoke in vaine, which were impiety once to imagine.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Then fourthly) if your aſſerſion be true, which is in effect thus, that all the Commands, (whether juſt, or unjuſt, or elſe you had as good ſaid nothing) if the Parliament muſt be obeyed, and ſo make them an unbounded Parliament, and without all Law, which is more t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n ever they deſired themſelves, then will you make a cleare antipathy, and disproportion, betwixt this of <hi>Pauls,</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Hoſea,</hi> and <hi>Micah,</hi> with divers other Texts, which Scriptures decipher very truly the Apoſtles meaning, and freeth him from your groſſe imputation. The Prophet <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſea</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ephraim</hi> is oppreſſed, and broken in Judgement,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſea</hi> 5.11. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 16.26.</note> and the reaſon is, becauſe he willingly walked after the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement: Now what thoſe Commands were, examine but the 1. <hi>Kings,</hi> where it is ſaid, that <hi>Omri</hi> (King of <hi>Iſrael</hi>) wrought evill in the eyes of the Lord, and did worſe then all that were before him; for he walked in all the way of <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> the Son of <hi>Nobat,</hi> and in his ſin, wherewith he made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſin, to provoke the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to anger with his vanities: From both which places you may obſerve, that it was not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accounted to <hi>Iſrael</hi> for a ſin, to obey the unjuſt Councell and Commands of King <hi>Omri,</hi> though their lawfull King, but that they ſhould alſo be attended with the deſert of ſin, to wit, to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:116163:21"/>be oppreſſed, and broken in iudgment, &amp;c. And that which confirmed both theſe places,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Micah</hi> 6. <hi>from</hi> 13. <hi>to</hi> 16.</note> is that of <hi>Micah,</hi> where he threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that they ſhall eate and not be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, ſow but not reape, &amp;c. and in the laſt verſe he gives the reaſon thereof, in theſe words; for the Statutes of <hi>Omri</hi> are kept, and all the workes of the houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> and ye walke in their Councels, that I ſhould make thee a deſolation and the Inhabitants thereof an hiſſing, therefore ye ſhall beare the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of my people.</p>
            <p>Now how ſhall theſe Prophets and the Apoſtle be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, unleſſe <hi>Pauls</hi> meaning in that place is, that obedience muſt be given to the juſt Law of a Kingdome, and onely to that; and that Magiſtrates muſt not be obeyed, in their unjuſt and illegall Commands, though lawfull Magiſtrates, for <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, they muſt be ſubject to the higher powers; the Prophet thunders out threatnings againſt them for being ſubject to unjuſt powers, though (as I ſaid before) a lawful Magiſtrate. So that it is clear, that the Apoſtles meaning is not, that ſubjection muſt be given to mens perſons or perſonall Commands,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 28.4. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> but to thoſe higher Powers, (to wit) the Law of the Kingdome wherewith men are intruſted, ſome with one part, ſome with another, and ought not to exceede the limits thereof.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Iames,</hi> upon this very ground, when he was arreſted for debt, told the Officer, that he who made Lawes, muſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe obey Lawes, and thereupon payd the debt, and never bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him that arreſted him, for ſo doing. From all that is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in this particular, the enſuing Syllogiſmes, are inevitably extracted.</p>
            <list>
               <head>1.</head>
               <item>Paul <hi>ſaith that every Soule muſt be ſubject to the higher Powers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>But King, Parliament, and all other Magiſtrates are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the limits of that number.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ergo, <hi>King and Parliament muſt be ſubject to the higher Powers.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:116163:21"/>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>All powers that are not given, are not of God.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>But Powers uſurped are not given.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ergo, <hi>Powers uſurped are not of God.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>3</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Every ſoule ought to be ſubject to the Higher Powers given, and to none elſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>But theſe Higher Powers that are uſurped, are not given.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ergo, <hi>No ſoule ought to be ſubject to Higher Powers not given.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>4</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thoſe Powers that be not given from God, are no powers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>But uſurped Powers are not given from God.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ergo, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurped Powers are no Powers.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>5</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thoſe Powers that are no Powers, ought not to be obeyed.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>But uſurped Powers are no Powers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ergo, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurped Powers ought not to be obeyed.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The probation of theſe Arguments, is evident from the very Words of the Apoſtle and Prophets, in the places before quated: therefore I will not ſpend time (my ordinary employments not ſuffering me) any longer therein; only give me leave to digreſſe a little, and obſerve (as I deſire alſo the Courteous Reader would) ſome paſſages of Scripture, which (in my ordinary rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding) I have met withall, very conſiderable for all mens obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, eſpecially thoſe in Authority; wherein all my behold, what the diſmall ends of thoſe Magiſtrates are, who take delight in oppreſſion and unrighteouſneſſe; I ſhall name divers places, and refer them to the deliberate debate of the Reader, they are quoted in the Margent; I ſhall onely inſiſt a little on the laſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 27.13, 14, 15, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14 31 &amp; 22.16.22, 23. <hi>Mat</hi> 3 5. <hi>Amo.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>Am.</hi> 4.1. his words are theſe, <hi>Heare this word ye Kins of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhan, that are in the Mountain of</hi> Samaria, <hi>which oppreſſe the poore, which cruſh the needy, which ſay to their Maſters, Bring, and let us drinke:</hi> This Prophet, though ſomewhat myſterious, and meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoricall here, yet, compared with other places, will bee made more cleere, and intelligible: By theſe Kine, <hi>Hoſea</hi> meanes, the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:116163:22"/>fore-mentioned <hi>Omri,</hi> which the other wicked Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and their pernicious Councels: for it was that <hi>Omri</hi> that bought this Hill Samaria, of one <hi>Shemer,</hi> for ten talents of ſilver, and built there on the City Samaria, where he lived, dyed, and was buried. Thoſe were they who oppreſſed the poore, and cruſhed the needy, which ſaid to their<note n="*" place="margin">In ſome tranſlations to their Lords. <hi>1</hi> King. <hi>16.24.28.</hi> Mark that expreſſion.</note> Maſters (to wit) (the oppreſſed poore, and cruſhed needy) <hi>Bring, and let us drinke.</hi> But what was the iſſue of all this? <hi>The Lord God hath ſworne by his Holineſſe</hi> (a greater oath could he not ſweate) that lo the dayes ſhall come upon you that he will take you away with bookt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>and your</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">A ſore judgment. v. <hi>3.</hi> Strange po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting from the judgment of God, as in Rev. <hi>6.15, 16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Poſterity with fiſh-bookt. And ye ſhall go out at the breeches, every Cow at that which is before her, and ye ſhall caſt them into the Palace</hi> (ſome tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations have it, <hi>caſt away the things of the Palace</hi>) ſaith the Lord. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>Thus much by way of digreſſion, let us now proceed to what followeth, which you lay down thus;</p>
            <p>For the great complaints made to them, although it were falſe that is reported [as I have cauſe to believe] That men are ſent from the Army to get hands to Petitions to themſelves, thereby to draw the eyes of the people after them; yet I doe conceive ſuch Petitions ought not to be received by any, who either by Proteſtation, or Covenant, have ſworn to mean the juſt power and priviledges of the Parliament, to whom of right it doth belong to heare, and determine, all the grievances of the people, not remediable in other Ordinary Courts of Juſtice.</p>
            <p>I perceive now, that although you want true matter to tax<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Army with, yet you want not ill-will enough, to inſiſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on reports, that are meerly groundleſſe, (which I feare did firſt, ariſe from your own braine; nor is there any but will marvell at you, for undertaking to examine the lawfulneſſe of the Armies proceedings, and then to bottome your Examination upon bare and unjuſt reports.</p>
            <p>This is capable of no other Anſwer (it being ſo untrue) but to aſſure you, and the Kingdome, that you have wronged the Army herein, and I fear that this is but a meer complement, framed to hold up your groundleſſe diſcourſe; and am apt to thinke, that if you had any ſuch thing againſt the Army, they ſhould have heard of it with open mouth ere this day; but (bleſſed be God) that the mouths of gain-ſayers are ſtopt.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:116163:22"/>
            <p>You proceed and ſay, There (meaning the Houſe) the people may be heard, without the forcible recommendation of an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; I wiſh you would tell the Kingdome, when the Army did by force, recommend any Petition, or thruſt on thoſe things that upon ſerious debate, have beene rejected, as prejudiciall to the Publique, as you affirme: or elſe you will bring ſuch a calumnie upon your ſelfe for theſe reports (and in print too) without the leaſt probation of them, in any circumſtance of time, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that (were your Name to your Booke) you could never wipe off againe.</p>
            <p>Now to the laſt clauſe in this part of your Examination, I only ſay this, That the Army never gave encouragements to ſuch Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions, nor Went about to ſet themſelves as a new Tribunal, which is, and ought to be believed, till the contrary be proved by you who accuſe them, which will never be, whileſt the Sun and Moon indure. Now wee will goe forward to the next place.</p>
            <p>For the examples of <hi>Scotland, Netherlands, Portugal,</hi> and ſome proceedings in this Parliament, which you urge for your War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, I muſt anſwer ingenerall, that preſidents are poore proofes, to juſtifie actions; and if admitted, there is nothing ſo bad, that might not obtain ſuch a Iuſtification; It is a warrant from ſome law, that muſt make every action lawfull. And although my bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe be not to ſearch into the grounds, or proceedings, upon which other Nations have taken up armes; yet, being called un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, I muſt cleere the miſapplication to <hi>Scotland,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, that your examination is full of miſappre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions, and you make your miſtakes, the Armies meaning; who intended not that examples ſhould be proofes, but preſidents, neither do they diminiſh ought from the lawfulneſſe of their Cauſe (for <hi>Exempla illuſtrant, non reſtringunt Legeem</hi>) and that they ground not the lawfulneſſe of their actions on them, but upon their Commiſſion, and the Parliaments owne Expoſition of the Law, in their Declarations frequently communicated to them, which Commiſſion, and Declarations, are their ſufficient Warrants, as formerly manifeſted.</p>
            <p>And now you have done all you can to divide the Parliament and Army, you would divide the Army from the Scots, by falſly
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:116163:23"/>charging the Army with a miſapplication to <hi>Scotland;</hi> you ſay, (but I know not who will believe you) that you are called (by whom I cannot imagine) to cleare the miſapplication to <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> To this I anſwer diſtinctly.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That you have taken in hand is of publique concernment, and therefore it requires a publique call, and who ſhould give this publique call beſides the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> I am ignorant of. But if they did give you a call, [me thinkes] they ſhould patronize it, and not ſuffer it to go abroad into the wide world to deceive, without either authority or name. But [let the Kingdome conſider, and they will ſcarce credit your looſe reports] how great a prejudice it would be to the honour, both of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and that of <hi>Scotland,</hi> that a private man ſhould be entruſted, with ſo publique a buſineſſe, when they have both ſo many wiſe and judicious men in both Aſſemblies, who know what their own intents and proceedings at the beginning were, and can better free themſelves from miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>applications [if any were] then any one in <hi>England,</hi> that is, in a manner, a ſtranger to them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Againe, I will here lay downe verbatim all that the Army have ſpoken of the Scots, in their Declaration, which will more manifeſtly diſcover your envie, and vindicate the Army from your aſperſion, theſe are their words, That the Souldiery may lawfully hold the hands of that Generall who will turne his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non againſt his Army, on purpoſe to deſtroy them; The Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men the hands of that Pilot, who wilfully runs his ſhip upon a Rock (as our Brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi> argued) this is one thing the Army have ſpoken of them, and if there be not more for the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification of the Scots here, then miſapplication of their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings at firſt, the weakeſt wit can ſoon determine.</p>
            <p>Another paſſage wherein the name of <hi>Scotland</hi> is uſed, is this, and theſe two are all they ſay of them. And truly ſuch King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, as have according both to the Law of Nature, and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, appeared to the vindication, and defence of their juſt rights, and liberties, have proceeded much higher, as our Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> who in the firſt beginning of theſe late differences, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociated in Covenant, from the very ſame grounds and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, (having no viſible forme, either of Parliament or King
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:116163:23"/>to countenance them) and as they were therein juſtified and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected by their own, and this Kingdome alſo, to we juſtly expect to be.</p>
            <p>Of the proceedings of <hi>Scotland</hi> in the particuler, the Army neither have, nor can make any application at all; becauſe the Scots had no viſible forme, either of King or Parliament, to countenance them at the beginning; but this Army had the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> onely their ſights were vailed by the ſubtill interpoſition of miſapprehenſions; by the impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Members of their confederates, untill they were removed: ſo that the Army can make no application at all, (and therefore no miſapplication in this particular) for the cauſe aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But grant the Scots had the Countenance of the Eſtates of <hi>Scotland:</hi> ſo had this Army the favour of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> (as ſhall be afterwards declared) onely their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings were obſtructed (as aforeſaid) by thoſe grand ſtumbling blocks, the accuſed Members, therefore if the Army had oppoſed their caſe to <hi>Scotland,</hi> then (I pray) what miſapplication were there here.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Then againe, if both theſe were granted for truth, firſt, that the multitude in <hi>Scotland,</hi> had the countenance of the Magiſtrates thereof. Secondly, that the Army in <hi>England,</hi> had not the favour of the Magiſtrates of that Kingdome; yet this ſhift alſo, would faile you; for the Parliaments of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that obedience binds not men to cut their own threates, and alſo, that oppoſition to the perſonall Commands of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, though accompanied with their preſence, if it be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Lawes, and authority, but in maintenance thereof, is not oppoſition againſt them, but defence of them, and upon this very ground, and for this cauſe, the <hi>Scots</hi> (though as ſtrictly bound to the contrary, as this Doctrine is to oppoſe the Parliament) tooke up Armes againſt their King at the beginning; whereby, and by what is before ſpoken (relation being thereunto had) it appeares there is no ſuch miſapplication to the <hi>Scots,</hi> (as your diſcourſe imports) in the maine, which is the defence of the Kingdome, and the juſt rights, powers, and priviledges of the people; but onely in circumſtance, which is the want of favour to the Magiſtrates of the Kingdome, which is not ſo conſiderable,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:116163:24"/>when it is put in the ballance, with the<note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 12.16 <hi>Lev.</hi> 24.20. <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.24, 25. <hi>Deut.</hi> 19.21 <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.38.</note> weale, &amp; preſervation of the Republike. Nature will indeavour to preſerve it ſelfe, and therefore gives all Creatures meanes, and wayes, and puts them in a capacity to uſe them, for their own defence againſt violence, vaſſalage,<note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 12.16 <hi>Lev.</hi> 24.20. <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.24, 25. <hi>Deut.</hi> 19.21 <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.38.</note> breach for breach, eye for eye, tooth for tooth, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="5">5. This examination is confuted as unlawfull by the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of reaſon, which ſaith that <hi>nihil quod eſt contra rationem eſt diſputandum;</hi> &amp; if this be not clearely <hi>contra rationem,</hi> I know not what is; for you go about to undoe that, which never was done, or empty a veſſell that never was full, to vindicate the <hi>Scots,</hi> and Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> from a miſapplication, when there was none at all made.</p>
            <p n="6">6. But this I believe is your great aime, (if any were ſo raſh as credit you) to divide the people of this Kingdome from the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, by ſuggeſting to them that the Army have not that favour, and countenance of the Magiſtracie, of this Kingdome, as the <hi>Scots</hi> had of that, and that the Army would tax the <hi>Scots</hi> with want of countenance from the Magiſtrates of that Kingdom, the better to juſtifie their own preſent actions; whereby you would render the Army odious, and force the people to believe them to be lawleſſe, and proceed in unwarrantable courſes, againſt, and without the knowledge, or conſent of the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> that ſo upon theſe grounds you may with more facility perſwade the Country and Kingdome, to band themſelves, and deſtroy them. But that the people may be undeceived, you reproved, and the Army juſtified, it is apparent, that one of theſe two things you aime at.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Either to make the 11 impeached Members the ſupreame Councell of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Or, that this Parliament which now ſit are no Parliament, and ſo have nothing to do with the Government of the Land. If you can prove the firſt of theſe that <hi>Maſſie,</hi> with his accomplices, were the ſupreame Councell of the Land, then indeed, you caſt, and overthrow the Army, for they never had the leaſt favour, or countenance from them, not was it ever deſired in all, or any part of their Actions.</p>
            <p>But if you will acknowledge the Gentlemen who now ſit in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:116163:24"/>the Houſe, to be the ſupreame Court, then I tell you, (and the whole Kingdom) that the Army have their favour, and furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, (both acting according to the tenour of the Law) in their actions hitherto; or elſe why did they declare them their Army, conferr ſuch dignities, and Honours on Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> of late, and when they met with uncivill oppoſition in their Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary proceedings, make them their <hi>ulrimum refugium:</hi> And when the people come to heare this, that the Armie have acted according to the rules of Law, for their freedoms, and alſo that they have the Parliaments countenance therein, they will give you but ſmall thankes for blinding their eyes, and will be apt to retaine, as they ought a better, and higher conceite, and eſteeme of the Army.</p>
            <p>Having ſhewed the grounds whereon the Parliament procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to the raiſing of an Army, you ſay, that upon this occaſion, and juſt quarrell, they raiſed ſeverall Armies, wherein were men of very great Honour, power, and intereſt in the Kingdome, It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares to be ſo by this Army, but (bleſſed be God) never any of their Armies (except what hath been done by this Army) did refuſe (that ever I heard of) to obey, when the Parliament (for the good and eaſe of the Kingdome, nay, although it were to lay them aſide, and raiſe others in their roome) commanded them to disband.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Here I anſwer firſt, that never any thing was propoſed to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Armies, as to the point of disbanding, before this Army was raiſed, and had by their fidelity and courage with the bleſſing of God upon their indeavours, made them uſeleſſe; and therefore how could you heare that refuſed that was never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Had there any thing of that nature been put to others before this Army was raiſed, I queſtion whether they, as well as this Army would not have refuſed it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It could not be accounted wiſdom in the Parliament to make any ſuch propoſall, to any of their Armies, before this was ſet forth, or at this time; their enemies being ſo ſtrong, and they ſo weake, as that ſomtimes they could not keepe the field, and when they were at the ſtrongeſt, they could ſpare none to disband.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:116163:25"/>
            <p n="4">4. But fourthly, if the point of disbanding had been propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and they willingly ſubmit thereto, they had not ſo much cauſe to the contrarie, as this Army hath: and therefore may bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſubmit to the Parliaments perſonal Commands, then this Army car; ſo that this appeares as groundles, as all the reſt. Then you ſay for thoſe inſtances of the Souldiers holding the hands of their Generall when he would turne his Cannon againſt his Army, and the Seamen, the hands of their Pilot, who willingly runs his Ship upon a Rock; I muſt ſay, that in thoſe and ſuch like caſes of ſurpriſall, or extreamity, where there is none to judge, nor no time or place for judgement, the danger being eminent, and the evill intention evident, the Law of nature doth teach, and juſtifie oppoſition, to the unjuſt, and tyrannous power of ſuperiours, in this is granted, all that can be expected, and therefore I will not ſpend time about it, and it was upon this very ground the Army proceeded, and proſecuted their late actions, the juſt rules of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture binding them thereunto. But ſomthing here wants clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, left by overſlipping thereof, you take advantage of further objection; you ſay, that in theſe and ſuch like caſes of ſurpriſall or extreamity, where there is none to judge, nor no time or place for judgement, the danger being eminent, and the evill intention evident, the law of nature doth teach, and juſtifie oppoſition, &amp;c. That the Army was ſurpriſed, and forced to an extreamity, is apparent by many particulars, I ſhall onely inſtance that, which the Army hath largely mentioned in their charge againſt the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached Members, if the reader pleaſe to looke into the Charge, it may give further ſatisfaction; I ſhall repeate ſome part of the 8. <hi>Article,</hi> where the Army charge Col. <hi>Harley,</hi> with a falſe let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which he brought into the Houſe, againſt his<note n="*" place="margin">Lieut. Colonell Pride.</note> Lieutenant Col. without any name to it, and in the laſt part of that S. Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, it is ſaid; and although the ſubſtance of the ſaid letter was moſt untrue, and no Authour thereof appeared, or could be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, although a Committee was appointed for examination thereof, and it was much preſſed the Authour ſhould be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered; yet the ſaid Col. <hi>Harley,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Clotworthy,</hi> and Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Waller,</hi> did ſo avow the reality of the ſaid letter, and that the contents thereof would be made good, as that thereby, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:116163:25"/>by other falſe ſuggeſtions of theirs againſt the Army, they procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Houſe upon long debate which held till about 8. of the clock at night, to order that a Committee of 5. Members (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the ſaid Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi> is one) ſhould prepare a Declaration to be brought into the Houſe the next morning, ſignifying the Houſes diſlike of the proceedings of the Army upon that Petition; as by the ſaid Order may appeare, upon which ſetling of the ſaid buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for that night, moſt of the Members departed, as conceive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing would be done thereupon, till the next day, and that then they might have a free debate concerning the ſame; but the Houſe ſtill continuing to ſit (upon diſpatch of ſome letters for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ordered) the ſaid Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi> by the ſame combination, and in further proſecution of the ſaid evill deſignes, having of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, without the Committee, prepared a Declaration againſt the Petition it ſelfe, contrary to the intention and direction of the ſaid order, and contrary to the rules of Juſtice, and uſuall courſe of Parliament, did the ſame night, about 10. of the clock, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to ſurprize the Houſe, preſent the ſame Declaration to the Houſe, whereby the ſaid Petitioners were without being heard, declared enemies to the State, and obſtructers of the reliefe of <hi>Ireland;</hi> if they perſiſted therein, as by the ſame Declaration, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation being thereunto had appeares, and did procure it to be then paſſed accordingly, to the great diſhonour of the Parliament, and their proceedings, to the inſufferable injury, the juſt provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, diſcouragement, and diſcontent of the Army, to the trouble and danger of the whole Kingdome, to the hindering of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and other the evill conſequences, in the ſaid generall Charge expreſſed; now if this be not a ſurprizing the Army, and forcing them to the extreameſt exigencies, (when they are in this illegall inhumane manner declared enemies to the State, and obſtructers of the reliefe of <hi>Inelana,</hi> for no cauſe, but petitioning for theſe things, that relate to them as Souldiers) then let the Kingdome judge, but to proceed,</p>
            <p>You ſay where there is no Judge, nor no time or place for judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp;c. to this I anſwer, there were Judges, &amp; time &amp; place for Judgment, but thoſe Judges were overpowred, by the dangerous diſtilling influences, of the maliguant impeached Members, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by the former paſſages, and the Parliaments Order, which Members ſince they were removed, how peaceably have the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:116163:26"/>Parliament (<hi>England's</hi> Judges) and their Army concurred, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, there are yet ſome (though not ſo powerfull as the former) left amongſt them, (I hope they will not be ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to continue long) who would hinder the concord betwixt both parties, and retard the Parliament from executing juſtice, and judgment, and anſwering the Army in their faire and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table demands, for the Kingdome and themſelves.</p>
            <p>But now to the next clauſe which is this; The danger being eminent, and their ill intention evident the Law of Nature doth teach, and juſtifie oppoſition, to the unjuſt and tyrannous power of Superiours; It is apparent, that the former proceedings of the Parliament (by the perſwaſion of the accuſed Members) were eminently and evidently dangerous, and evill, to the Army (to the hazard of their eſtates who had any, loſſe of their due arreares, and forfeiture of their liberties, if not their very lives) therefore I will not ſtand to aggravate the buſineſſe now, it not agreeing with my nature and work to uſe tautologies, or inlarge my ſelfe by the needleſſe multiplication of words, which is condemned for vanity;</p>
            <p>The next thing you lay down thus; But it is no ground for a rule where a judgment may be had, or expected, as now in the caſe betwixt the Parliament and Army.</p>
            <p>This will ſtand you in as little ſtead as the reſt; For ſince thoſe pernicious ſpirits [who compaſſe Sea and Land to make a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelyte] have been ſeparated from the Parliament, there hath been no need of a judgment; for both Parliament and Army, do ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirably agree, without any apparent dangerous claſhing, or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition at all.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.2.</note> 
               <hi>When the righteous are in Authority the people re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce: but when the wicked beare the rule, the people mourne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place you ſay; Theſe inſtances might have beene more colourably to the point, if the Parliament had drawne out Forces againſt the Army, to have cut them off: then notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the obedience they owe to the Parliament, they might poſſible have defended themſelves againſt ſuch Force. There be many things in this aſſertion, that would have particular and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct anſwers, but I ſhall reply to your aſſumption in generall thus; That a piece of Ordinance is made for defence, as well as a Target, and it is as lawfull for the people of <hi>England,</hi> to invade the Countries of thoſe, who would ſurprize theirs, as to fight
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:116163:26"/>with them when they are landed; and it is as good policy to prepare for an enemy, though but darkly diſcovered, as to fight with them, upon never ſo great advantage, when they are nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er hand: And though the Parliament did not draw out Forces againſt the Army, yet ſome falſe Members of Parliament [not to wrong the innocent] endeavoured, not onely to raiſe Forces [contrary to the Law of this Kingdom] but alſo to draw thoſe that were deſigned for the reliefe of helpleſſ; <hi>Ireland</hi> [an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment more warrantable then the other] to a Randevoux at <hi>Reading;</hi> which place [moſt men know] is not the way from <hi>Briſtol, Cheſter,</hi> and other parts nigh the Sea Coaſts into <hi>Ireland,</hi> And what other deſigne they could have in it, but to engage them in a new warre againſt the Parliament and Army, is utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beyond my capacity, to apprehend, or conceive.</p>
            <p>For what followeth in this part of your Examination, I ſhall forbeare to trouble the Reader, or my ſelf with it, as being inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid, and impertinent to the work in hand.</p>
            <p>In the next place you ſay, For the laſt thing alleaged; That the Armies proceedings may be juſtified, when againſt injuſtice, unrighteouſneſſe, and miſcarriage in Government: If that were granted, and the Parliament were guilty in all [which I am moſt confident can never be made good by cleare inſtances, that they are guilty of any courſe of injuſtice, or unrighteouſneſſe, though all the World, and the accuſer of the Brethren to helpe ſhould ſet about it] yet that would not come up to juſtification of the Army, becauſe God hath not made them Judges for the people of the Kingdome, either of juſtice, or injuſtice, right or wrong; Some part of this which is bounded with a <hi>parentheſis,</hi> is ſpoken in a furious paſſion, as if it were impoſſible for the <hi>Parliament</hi> to erre: I am therefore regardleſſe of giving any anſwer unto it, the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.4.</note> wiſeman exhorting me thereunto.</p>
            <p>But then for the next thing, it is not my purpoſe, neither was it in the whole, or any part of this diſcourſe, to taxe the whole Aſſembly of Parliament, for that I well enough know, there are many Members in that Body very ſound, and faithful, who have to their powers withſtood all proceedings of injuſtice, unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and miſcarriage in Government: yet let me tell you, it is apparent enough to the whole Kingdome, that there have bin
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:116163:27"/>ſuch proceedings to the almoſt overthrow of State &amp; Kingdom: and where injuſtice, unrighteouſneſſe, &amp; miſcarriage in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be acted but in that Court, I know not; For all other Courts in the Kingdome are ſtrictly limited, and bounded, and over ſeen by the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> therefore cannot exceed thoſe Rules, that particularly relate to them, which are ſet down by the conſent of Parliament every other Court, acting, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in, and proſecuting ſeverall things, and at ſeverall times and places.</p>
            <p>But the High Court of Parliament, are Supreame, and have the hearing, deciding, and doing of all things in the Kingdome whether determinable, or not determinable in other inferiour Courts.</p>
            <p>Then you ſay, That though this were granted (which undou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>btedly muſt according to what I ſaid before) yet that would not come up to Juſtification of the Army, becauſe God hath not made them Judges for the people of the Kingdome, neither of juſtice, nor injuſtice, right or wrong. I have before made it appeare, that the Army by their Commiſſion (which clearely juſtifies them for ſo doing) are bound to oppoſe injuſtice, and wrong in the Parliament, as well as in the King, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther where they find it, the Parliaments own Declarations, and the Lawes of Nature leading them thereunto. And as to the point of Gods making them Judges, we are to conſider</p>
            <p n="1">1 That Judges are made by God, either immediately, and without the uſe of any meanes, or inſtruments; and then he calls them by ſpeaking (if I may uſe the Scripture phraſe) to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves particularly, and accommodating them with his ſpirit, for ſuch employments, as he did <hi>Ioſhuah, Othiniel, Ehud,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; or by giving his Miniſters, and other particular men no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice thereof, is he did to <hi>Samuel</hi> of <hi>Saul,</hi> and appointing him to anoint <hi>Saul,</hi> and for that purpoſe giving <hi>Saul</hi> a ſpirit of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie: but theſe are not Gods uſuall wayes now; nor can we inſtance in one that hath been ſo appointed, or ordained.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Or, ſecondly, God uſeth meanes, and inſtruments, in the creation and conſtitution of Judges, and other Officers of a Republique; which meanes, are</p>
            <p n="1">1 Ordinary, and that muſt be either</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:116163:27"/>
            <p n="1">1 A Succeſſion by Birth and Generation, and ſo the Lord Mayor of <hi>London's</hi> Son muſt be Lord Mayor, when his Father is dead.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Or, it muſt by the generall conſent, adviſe, and knowledge of the people, and thus the major part of the Parliament are lawfully choſen.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Or ſecondly, God uſeth extraor linary meanes, and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (as when Warre is in a Kingdome, the certaine token of ſucceeding ſorrow) Armies are raiſed to decide the controverſie with their Swords, betwixt both; each party being aſſured of his own juſt cauſe; and both wayting with a doubting confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, on which ſide the hovering Victory will reſolve to pitch her Trophees.</p>
            <p>And thus this Army was raiſed, (not ſo much to judge but under the conſiderations formerly mentioned, though you vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imagine by that meanes to brand them) as to execute the juſt Judgments, and Commandes of the Parliament (<hi>Englands</hi> chiefe Pretors.) And this the Army in caſes of neceſſity may do, being called thereunto by the very ſame power the Parliament were, as is formerly inſtanced, injuſtice, unrighteouſneſſe, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages in Government leading them, and the providence of God guiding them (by putting ſeaſons, and oportunities into their hands) thereunto.</p>
            <p>Alſo, the manner of their being Judges [if they muſt needes be ſo] conſidered, doth ſomwhat conſtraine them to their preſent actions; which is no otherwiſe then thus; they believe and ſay, that thoſe things which are juſt, and equitable, and tending to the Kingdomes weale; and ſo judged, and deemed (upon ſerious, deliberate debate) by the Parliament, are real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and truly ſo.</p>
            <p>And thereupon they reſolved to execute thoſe things ſo order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, acted, and judged by the Parliament, or to be executed themſelves, which reſolution (I hope, for the Kingdomes, and their own ſafety) they will ſtill continue, which (without any impoſibilities) they may do, whilſt proceeding upon thoſe ſound principles. And herein they do no more then the rules of nature and reaſon, (to which I am ſure, the Lawes of <hi>England</hi> are, or ought to be reduced &amp; do allow, for, <hi>Lex ſpectat naturae or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:116163:28"/>&amp; non cogit ad impoſibilia, ſed intendit ſemper, quod conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit rationi;</hi> the Law hath regard to the order of nature, and doth not command impoſſibilities, but intends, and purpoſes, what doth agree with reaſon; I ſhall ſay no more here but this, that if the Parliament judge, and declare, what the liberties, proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and priviledges of the ſubject is, (the contrary whereof is oppreſſion, injuſtice, and miſcarriage in goverement) then the Army may juſtifiably ſtand to it with their lives, againſt any, without reſpect to perſons.</p>
            <p>You ſay in the next place, when the people conceive any thing to be amiſſe, it is their duty to repreſent it to thoſe whom God hath appointed, to the Office, and place of Judgement.</p>
            <p>To this I ſadly, and conciſely anſwer, that there were many cries, but few eares to heare, or hearts to pitty them, and when the people did petition, they and their Petitions (as before is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced) were rejected, ſome burned. I wiſh it had been other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that ſo righteouſneſſe and juſt Judgement, might run down our ſtreetes like a mighty ſtreame, that every man might ſit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his own Vine, and under his own figtree; ſo had peace been within our Borders ere this day.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place you ſay; but if the meaning of this laſt part of it be, that God hath made the former ſucceſſes, and preſent power of the Army, a teſtimony to its oppoſing the pretended injuſtice, unrighteouſneſſe, and miſcarriage in government, then the Turk may have the ſame argument, to juſtifie his Title, to all he hath gotten in Chriſtendome. But the wiſe man teacheth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, that no man knoweth love or hatred by all that is afore him, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>In this, ſeverall things are conſiderable; but (for want of time) I ſhall anſwer in generall, and briefly; No, that this, as you have layd it downe, is not the meaning of that part of the Declaration, and though all in this were granted, that you would have; yet the evill conſequence you have drawn thence, would prove unſound, and feeble (the cauſe conſidered) for the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:116163:28"/>Turkes oppoſing the Chriſtians is for the enlargement of his Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories, and advancement of his Monarchy, and greatneſſe; but the diſproportion betwixt the Army and Parliament, was for the reſtoring, eſtabliſhing, and confirming the immunities, &amp; freedomes of the freeborne people of <hi>England,</hi> (the Parliament declaring at firſt what they were, which was all they could do then of themſelves) and the Army (neither regarding the pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted favour, of pretended friends, nor civill force of their publike enemies) ſtoutly contending with their lives in their hands, for them; yet now invaded by ſome putrified rotten Members, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the intent, and meaning of the Houſe in their firſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations) are againe defended by the Army; and therefore this is no Argument at all for the juſtification of the Turkes Title to all he hath gotten in Chriſtendom.</p>
            <p>But then againe, as it appeares, that neither of the two former parts, of your examination, nor both of them together can make up the Armies meaning, in that part of their Declaration; ſo, I ſhall give you my underſtanding of it; they ſay, that ſupreame end (the glory of God) which all men ſhould eſpecially aime at; is not wanting in theſe caſes, but they ſtudy, how, by all meanes to advance it, the better to ſet a price upon all ſuch proceedings of righteouſneſſe, and juſtice; It (to wit) the glory of God; being one witneſſe of God in the world; that is, one maine argument to diſcover the candid, and ſincere purpoſes of them, who make that their marke, to carrie on a Teſtimonie againſt the injuſtice, and unrighteouſneſſe of men, whatever they be; and againſt the miſcarriage of Governments, whereſoever it is found; when corrupted, or declining from their primitive, and originall glorie; that is, when they are tranſported from their primarie brightneſſe, and luſtre, into the muddie ſtreames of diſorder, oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and miſcarriage: The ſcope of all is this. That the glorie of God it (being their ultimate end) is a teſtimonie of their proceedings, againſt all injuſtice, it being the cleareſt demonſtration, of the reall and upright parpoſes, and reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of any.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:116163:29"/>
            <p>And to conclude, the Army might ſay, as<note n="*" place="margin">Iuliamus Emperor of Rome, ſlaine in the Pers. Warres.</note> one did on his Death-bed; Right joyfull, and wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tingly much more, have I ſtood firmly grounded, and reſolute, whenſoever the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, as an imperious mother hath expoſed me, to apparent and evident danger, as one uſed to contemn the whirling ſtormes of all caſualties.</p>
            <p>I have now ended this part of your examination, and do ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſire, it may give you and other doubting friends that ſatisfaction deſired, it being publiſhed for that purpoſe.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="queries">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:116163:29"/>
            <head>Certain Quaeries wherein Reſolution is deſired, propoſed without any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular by-intereſts, or private reſpects at all, but for ſatisfaction.</head>
            <p n="1">I. WHether the Army under the preſent conduct of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> are not as well bound to reſiſt (yea to the death) Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie and Oppreſſion in the Parliament, as in the King; and whether every point and part of their Commiſſion, extend not as well to the one, as the other.</p>
            <p n="2">II. How the Army can disband, till they ſee thoſe things effected, for which the people entruſted them in Military Employments?</p>
            <p n="3">III. Whether the end of their Banding was to free nd acquit the people of this Kingdome from feared ſlavery or not? if it were, how will Conſcience, and the Kingdome be ſatisfied, if they disband before they have done their worke? if not, then why were they raiſed?</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Whether the effect, or end of any thing is not more honourable, and conſequently to be preferred before, the efficient cauſe whereby it was procured?</p>
            <p n="5">V. Whether the blood of all the ſlayne during the late Warre, may not be required juſtly at the hands of this Army, (ſince it was ſpilt
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:116163:30"/>in vaine) if they endeavour not to bring to paſſe the juſt ends for which it was ſhed?</p>
            <p n="6">VI. Whether a lawfull Cauſe, a lawfull Commiſſion, and the peoples willingneſſe, in caſes of neceſſity, be not ſufficient to raiſe a lawfull Army?</p>
            <p n="7">VII. Whether the Parliaments lawfull Ordinances are not ſufficient warrants for the Army, in the proſecution of the Kingdomes Cauſe, in the caſe aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. Whether the Army are bound to obſerve the will and Command of the Parliament, when they are acted by a principle of egoity, and ſelfiſhnes and for private Cauſes, and intereſts, or the will and Commands of the Law?</p>
            <p n="9">IX. Whether the Parliament are better able to judge of the peoples grievances, and oppreſſions then they be of their own?</p>
            <p n="10">X. Whether the Parliament are not bound to heare and give ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory anſwers to their Petitions? and whether it be a breach of privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (as they have ſomtimes declared) ſo to do, or not?</p>
            <p n="11">XI. Whether the priviledges of Parliament, be inconſiſtent with the weale of the people?</p>
            <p n="12">XII. Whether upon non-ſatisfaction to the juſt Demands of the people, no reaſon given but breach of priviledge, the Army are not engaged, both by Covenant and Command, to uſe all lawfull meanes for the procurement of the peoples reaſonable Deſires, they having employed, and maintained them for that purpoſe?</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. Whether the Parliaments expreſſion in the Declaration former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mentioned <hi>(to wit)</hi> that obedience binds not men to cut their owne throats, and thoſe ſo frequently uſed in Scripture, <hi>ſave thy ſelfe, thy wife, thy children, an eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth:</hi> be not juſt grounds for the preſent actions of the Army, and why?</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:116163:30"/>
            <p n="14">XIV. Whether an Act of Indempnity (though with the Royall aſſent for things done <hi>in tempore &amp; loco belli,</hi> be ſufficient to acquit the Army from thoſe things they have done, <hi>neque in tempore, nec loco belli,</hi> eſpecially the Parliament having (upon no grounds in the earth) declared them Traytors &amp; enemies, <hi>in tempore pacis?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">XV. Whether the King and Parliament are not both ſubordinate to the Law? And whether is Supreame, the King or Parliament, the Head or his Members? if the King, then why might not the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the Parliament be as warrantably oppoſed, as the Kings?</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:116163:31"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:116163:31"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
